<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Computational Quantum Science</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/</link><description>Recent content on Computational Quantum Science</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</managingEditor><webMaster>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 07:45:41 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.computational-quantum.science/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Many-body dynamics with explicitly time-dependent neural quantum states</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/27_tnqs/</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 07:45:41 +0100</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/27_tnqs/</guid><description>&lt;p>Simulating the dynamics of many-body quantum systems is a significant challenge, especially in higher dimensions where entanglement grows rapidly. Neural quantum states (NQS) offer a promising tool for representing quantum wavefunctions, but their application to time evolution faces scaling challenges. We introduce the time-dependent neural quantum state (t-NQS), a novel approach incorporating explicit time dependence into the neural network ansatz. This framework optimizes a single, time-independent set of parameters to solve the time-dependent Schrödinger equation across an entire time interval. We detail an autoregressive, attention-based transformer architecture and techniques for extending the model&amp;rsquo;s applicability. To benchmark and demonstrate our method, we simulate quench dynamics in the 2D transverse field Ising model and the time-dependent preparation of the 2D antiferromagnetic state in a Heisenberg model, demonstrating state of the art performance, scalability, and extrapolation to unseen intervals. These results establish t-NQS as a powerful framework for exploring quantum dynamics in strongly correlated systems.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Roughening dynamics of interfaces in two-dimensional quantum matter</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/26_roughening/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 12:01:49 +0100</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/26_roughening/</guid><description>&lt;p>The properties of interfaces are key to understand the physics of matter. However, the study of quantum interface dynamics has remained an outstanding challenge. Here, we use large-scale Tree Tensor Network simulations to identify the dynamical signature of an interface roughening transition within the ferromagnetic phase of the 2D quantum Ising model. For initial domain wall profiles we find extended prethermal plateaus for smooth interfaces, whereas above the roughening transition the domain wall decays quickly. Our results can be readily explored experimentally in Rydberg atomic systems.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Noé joined as new PhD student</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/21-noe_joined/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2024 15:23:09 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/21-noe_joined/</guid><description>&lt;p>With the beginning of October, 

&lt;a href="people/noe">Noé&lt;/a> joined our group as a new PhD student. He is going to work on our DFG project ``Machine Learning to Tailor Correlated States of Matter&amp;rsquo;'.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Computational quantum dynamics</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/teaching/24_computational_quantum_dynamics/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 18:21:34 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/teaching/24_computational_quantum_dynamics/</guid><description>&lt;p>Modern experiments employing ultrafast pump-probe techniques or quantum simulation are opening up the exciting realm of far-from-equilibrium quantum dynamics. These developments have directed theoretical attention to questions about thermalization, non-equilibrium phases of matter, and transient dynamical phenomena. Since analytical approaches are typically limited, numerical methods are key to understand the theoretical models. This lecture will cover a variety of computational tools for the simulation of quantum dynamics, namely:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Time-dependent single-particle Schrödinger equation
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Spectral methods&lt;/li>
&lt;li>PDE integration&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Non-interacting many-body systems
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Free fermions&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Bogoliubov transformation&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Interacting many-body systems
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Exact diagonalization&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Semiclassical approaches&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Tensor network methods&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Neural quantum states&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Throughout the course, we will implement these methods in exercises and interactive sessions. The resulting codes will be used to investigate a variety of quantum dynamical phenomena, such as&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Noé Salmeron</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/people/noe/</link><pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2024 20:04:39 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/people/noe/</guid><description>&lt;p>Hi, I’m Noe!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m currently focused on developing efficient numerical techniques to simulate and study Floquet systems. My work involves leveraging machine learning methods, particularly neural network quantum states, together with theoretical insights to improve these simulations. More broadly, I’m interested in numerical approaches for studying complex systems in quantum physics.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="short-cv">Short CV&lt;/h2>
&lt;table>
 &lt;thead>
 &lt;tr>
 &lt;th style="text-align: left">&lt;/th>
 &lt;th style="text-align: left">&lt;/th>
 &lt;/tr>
 &lt;/thead>
 &lt;tbody>
 &lt;tr>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">since 2024&lt;/td>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">PhD student at University of Regensburg and IMPRS-QDC&lt;/td>
 &lt;/tr>
 &lt;tr>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">2022-2024&lt;/td>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">Master in physics at EPFL&lt;/td>
 &lt;/tr>
 &lt;tr>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">2019-2022&lt;/td>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">Bachelor in physics at EPFL&lt;/td>
 &lt;/tr>
 &lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table></description></item><item><title>Moksh Bhateja</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/people/moksh/</link><pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2024 20:03:48 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/people/moksh/</guid><description>&lt;p>Hello!! I&amp;rsquo;m Moksh, a master&amp;rsquo;s student with academic interests in theoretical and computational condensed matter physics, the dynamics of quantum many-body systems, and machine learning. Currently, I am researching the evolution and dynamics of quantum systems, focusing on the spatial and temporal behavior of entanglement in many-body systems through an information theory framework. Recreationally, I enjoy watching movies, listening to music, traveling, swimming, and drawing portraits.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="short-cv">Short CV&lt;/h2>
&lt;table>
 &lt;thead>
 &lt;tr>
 &lt;th style="text-align: left">&lt;/th>
 &lt;th style="text-align: left">&lt;/th>
 &lt;/tr>
 &lt;/thead>
 &lt;tbody>
 &lt;tr>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">since 2024&lt;/td>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">Intern at FZ Jülich (PGI-8) and University of Regensburg, Germany&lt;/td>
 &lt;/tr>
 &lt;tr>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">2024&lt;/td>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">Intern at Queen&amp;rsquo;s University, Canada&lt;/td>
 &lt;/tr>
 &lt;tr>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">2024&lt;/td>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">Intern at Lille University &amp;amp; Sorbonne University, France&lt;/td>
 &lt;/tr>
 &lt;tr>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">2023&lt;/td>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">Intern at Jet Propulsion Laboratory - NASA, Caltech&lt;/td>
 &lt;/tr>
 &lt;tr>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">since 2020&lt;/td>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">B.Tech.+Masters in Solid State Physics at Indian institute of Space Science and Technology (IIST)&lt;/td>
 &lt;/tr>
 &lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table></description></item><item><title>Nikita Alert</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/people/nikita/</link><pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2024 20:03:48 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/people/nikita/</guid><description>&lt;p>Hi, I am Nikita.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I am a Master student and for my project I will use neural networks to efficeinty store wave functions of many body systems. I am just starting, but ready to go down the rabbit hole.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="short-cv">Short CV&lt;/h2>
&lt;table>
 &lt;thead>
 &lt;tr>
 &lt;th style="text-align: left">&lt;/th>
 &lt;th style="text-align: left">&lt;/th>
 &lt;/tr>
 &lt;/thead>
 &lt;tbody>
 &lt;tr>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">2023 - &lt;/td>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">    Studies at the University of Cologne, Master in Computational Sciences (Condensed Matter Physics)&lt;/td>
 &lt;/tr>
 &lt;tr>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">2019 – 2023&lt;/td>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">   Studies at the University of Cologne, Bachelor in Physics&lt;/td>
 &lt;/tr>
 &lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table></description></item><item><title>Workshop on NQS for dynamics coming up</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/20-nqs_workshop/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2024 14:09:43 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/20-nqs_workshop/</guid><description>&lt;p>In November we&amp;rsquo;ll be hosting a workshop on simulating the non-equilibrium dynamics with neural quantum states here in Regensburg. See the 

&lt;a href="https://events.hifis.net/event/1752" target="_blank">workshop website&lt;/a> for more information!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Neural Quantum States and Peaked Molecular Wave Functions: Curse or Blessing?</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/25_peaked_nqs/</link><pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2024 18:50:55 +0100</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/25_peaked_nqs/</guid><description>&lt;p>The field of neural quantum states has recently experienced a tremendous progress, making them a competitive tool of computational quantum many-body physics. However, their largest achievements to date mostly concern interacting spin systems, while their utility for quantum chemistry remains yet to be demonstrated. Two main complications are the peaked structure of the molecular wave functions, which impedes sampling, and large number of terms in second quantised Hamiltonians, which hinders scaling to larger molecule sizes. In this paper we address these issues jointly and argue that the peaked structure might actually be key to drastically more efficient calculations. Specifically, we introduce a novel algorithm for autoregressive sampling without replacement and a procedure to calculate a computationally cheaper surrogate for the local energy. We complement them with a custom modification of the stochastic reconfiguration optimisation technique and a highly optimised GPU implementation. As a result, our calculations require substantially less resources and exhibit more than order of magnitude speedup compared to the previous works. On a single GPU we study molecules comprising up to 118 qubits and outperform the ``golden standard&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo; CCSD(T) benchmark in Hilbert spaces of about 10^15 Slater determinants, which is orders of magnitude larger than what was previously achieved. We believe that our work underscores the prospect of NQS for challenging quantum chemistry calculations and serves as a favourable ground for the future method development.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Master's project: Fermionic neural quantum states</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/joinus/projects/2024-fermion_nqs/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 13:28:07 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/joinus/projects/2024-fermion_nqs/</guid><description>&lt;p>A central objective of our work is the advancement of numerical simulation techniques based on 

&lt;a href="https://www.computational-quantum.science/research/neural_quantum_states/">neural quantum states&lt;/a> (NQS). The underlying idea of this approach is to tackle the quantum curse of dimensionality by exploiting the proven merit of artificial neural networks for dealing with high-dimensional data. This new numerically exact technique can overcome existing limitations of established computational methods. Thereby, it will open up intriguing physical regimes for numerical simulation, such as correlated electrons, which are confined to two spatial dimensions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The goal of this project is investigate a disorder-driven insulator-superconductor transition. Generally, disorder in metals leads to a localization of the electronic wave function in the system and thus, to the transition from a conductor to an insulator. Similarly, it has been suggested that disorder in superconducting systems can drive the breakdown of the superconducting phase and the emergence of an insulating phase. A full simulation of such situations including all quantum correlations, however, still open.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Jonas distinguished as Young Excellent Scientist</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/19-jonas-distinction/</link><pubDate>Wed, 26 Jun 2024 14:09:43 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/19-jonas-distinction/</guid><description>&lt;p>Our Postdoc 

&lt;a href="https://www.computational-quantum.science/people/jonas/">Jonas&lt;/a> has secured one of the five places in 

&lt;a href="https://www.fz-juelich.de/en/research/young-scientists/young-excellent-scientist-program" target="_blank">FZ Jülich&amp;rsquo;s Young Excellent Scientist Program (YESP)&lt;/a>. The program offers individual support modules, among which the funding to hold their own symposium on a topic of their choice. Congratulations, Jonas!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Opening for PhD position</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/18-phd-opening/</link><pubDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2024 19:00:34 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/18-phd-opening/</guid><description>&lt;p>We are looking for a new PhD student for a DFG-funded project on &amp;ldquo;machine learning to tailor correlated states of matter&amp;rdquo;. The project in cooperation with colleagues at 

&lt;a href="https://pks.mpg.de" target="_blank">MPI PKS&lt;/a> will evolve around 

&lt;a href="https://www.computational-quantum.science/research/neural_quantum_states/">neural quantum states&lt;/a> for non-equilibrium quantum many-body physics.&lt;/p>
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Update:&lt;/strong> The position has been filled.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>PhD position: Neural quantum states for non-equilibrium quantum many-body physics</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/joinus/jobs/2024-phd/</link><pubDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2024 13:28:07 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/joinus/jobs/2024-phd/</guid><description>&lt;p>The research of our &amp;ldquo;Computational quantum science&amp;rdquo; research group is directed at understanding and controlling the collective dynamics of quantum many-body systems far from equilibrium, which may ultimately pave the way to devise new technologies that rely on the quantum laws of nature. For investigations based on microscopic model systems one has to devise strategies to deal with the curse of dimensionality inherent to the quantum many-body problem. Particularly challenging is the development of efficient and versatile computational methods that serve as crucial link between experimental observations and theoretical models. For this purpose, we employ machine learning methods, which are for example well suited to represent the many-body wave function in a compressed form.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Our group is based at the 

&lt;a href="https://www.uni-regensburg.de/en" target="_blank">University of Regensburg&lt;/a> and furthermore affiliated with 

&lt;a href="https://www.fz-juelich.de/en/pgi/pgi-8" target="_blank">PGI-8 at Forschungszentrum Jülich&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Introducing wave function networks</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/17-wfn-published/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Jun 2024 14:19:31 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/17-wfn-published/</guid><description>&lt;p>The advent of quantum simulators and computers has made projective measurement a reality at the many-particle level: Experiments routinely collect high-quality pictures of wave functions made of hundreds of components. But the wealth of information obtained challenges traditional theoretical modeling, which often focuses on a few observables. In our work, that is now 

&lt;a href="https://journals.aps.org/prx/abstract/10.1103/PhysRevX.14.021029" target="_blank">published in Phys. Rev. X&lt;/a>, we introduce a framework to describe wave-function measurements using network theory, enabling the discovery of a very deep inner structure in quantum wave functions: scale-freeness similar to other completely disconnected ensembles, such as those found in communication, social networks and the internet.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Opening for student assistant</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/16-shk-opening/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 May 2024 11:15:17 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/16-shk-opening/</guid><description>&lt;p>We are lookging for a dedicated student assistant to support our research team. The main tasks will evolve around programming and conducting explorative studies in the area of machine learning for quantum science.&lt;/p>
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Update:&lt;/strong> The position has been filled.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Student assistant in machine learning for quantum science</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/joinus/jobs/2024-shk/</link><pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2024 18:28:07 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/joinus/jobs/2024-shk/</guid><description>&lt;p>We are currently looking for a dedicated student assistant to support our research team. The main tasks will evolve around programming and conducting explorative studies in the area of machine learning for quantum science.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Requirements:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Solid programming skills in Python or Julia&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Basic knowledge of quantum mechanics and statistical physics&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ideally, basic knowledge of machine learning, especially artificial neural networks&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Interest in learning more about the topics above&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ability to work independently&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Motivation to work in an international research team&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Enrollment at the University of Regensburg&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>How to apply:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you are interested in this position, don&amp;rsquo;t hesitate to contact 

&lt;a href="https://www.computational-quantum.science/people/markus">Markus&lt;/a> via e-mail. Please attach a current transcript of records and briefly sketch how you match the opening.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Learning Hamiltonians that describe non-equilibrium steady states</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/15-floquet-learning-published/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2024 17:45:40 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/15-floquet-learning-published/</guid><description>&lt;p>Periodic driving is a prime way to engineer quantum matter with interesting properties. For this purpose, it is essential to bring the system into metastable steady states, the properties of which governed by a corresponding effective Hamiltonian. We have developed a deep-learning-assisted variational algorithm to reconstruct such effective Hamiltonians from observations. Thereby, we could recover local Hamiltonians in pre-thermal regimes and observe the growing complexity of instantaneous effective Hamiltonians in subsequent heating regimes. Our findings are now published in 

&lt;a href="https://journals.aps.org/prresearch/abstract/10.1103/PhysRevResearch.6.023160" target="_blank">Phys. Rev. Research&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Physics meets information</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/teaching/24_physics_meets_info/</link><pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2024 21:21:34 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/teaching/24_physics_meets_info/</guid><description>&lt;p>Many-body physics and information theory share a rich interface with intriguing connections. First of all, any information has to be carried by physical objects and - accordingly - information processing has to follow the laws of physics. Moreover, the concept of information can itself become part of physical processes, leading to the conclusion that &amp;ldquo;information is physical&amp;rdquo;. From this perspective, the course will cover the following topics:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Entropy and the 2nd law of thermodynamics&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Information theory&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Thermodynamics: Maxwell demon and Landauer principle&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Statistical mechanics: Jaynes&amp;rsquo; principle and renormalization group&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Quantum information&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="materials">Materials&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>

&lt;a href="https://spur.uni-regensburg.de/qisserver/pages/startFlow.xhtml?_flowId=searchCourseNonStaff-flow&amp;amp;_flowExecutionKey=e1s3" target="_blank">SPUR&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>

&lt;a href="https://elearning.uni-regensburg.de/enrol/index.php?id=65729" target="_blank">Course materials in GRIPS&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>Observing fluctuation relations on a quantum processor</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/14-jarzynski-published/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Nov 2023 09:46:09 +0100</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/14-jarzynski-published/</guid><description>&lt;p>Jarzynski’s equality describes a relation in statistical physics between the fluctuations during a work process and the
thermal free energy difference corresponding to the initial and final ensemble. While Jarzynski’s equality has been
checked in many scenarios, previous experiments focused on systems with only a handful of degrees of freedom in the
quantum regime. In our collaboration with colleagues at MPI PKS, the University of Bonn, and UC Berkeley/LBNL, we probed
for the first time Jarzynski’s equality in the quantum many-body regime. We devise a dynamical protocol to measure work
on quantum computers using a suitably prepared thermal ensemble and tested Jarzynski&amp;rsquo;s equality on different quantum
processors with up to 16 qubits.
The article has now been 

&lt;a href="https://journals.aps.org/prx/abstract/10.1103/PhysRevX.13.041023" target="_blank">published in Phys. Rev. X&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Reinforcement learning pulses for transmon qubit entangling gates</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/24_transmon_rl/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Nov 2023 09:40:55 +0100</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/24_transmon_rl/</guid><description>&lt;p>The utility of a quantum computer depends heavily on the ability to reliably perform accurate quantum logic operations.
For finding optimal control solutions, it is of particular interest to explore model-free approaches, since their quality
is not constrained by the limited accuracy of theoretical models for the quantum processor - in contrast to many
established gate implementation strategies. In this work, we utilize a continuous-control reinforcement learning algorithm
to design entangling two-qubit gates for superconducting qubits; specifically, our agent constructs cross-resonance and CNOT
gates without any prior information about the physical system. Using a simulated environment of fixed-frequency,
fixed-coupling transmon qubits, we demonstrate the capability to generate novel pulse sequences that outperform the
standard cross-resonance gates in both fidelity and gate duration, while maintaining a comparable susceptibility to
stochastic unitary noise. We further showcase an augmentation in training and input information that allows our agent to
adapt its pulse design abilities to drifting hardware characteristics, importantly with little to no additional optimization.
Our results exhibit clearly the advantages of unbiased adaptive-feedback learning-based optimization methods for transmon
gate design.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Combined school and conference at ICTP</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/13-ictp-conference/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Oct 2023 09:33:01 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/13-ictp-conference/</guid><description>&lt;p>Together with colleagues from Hamburg, Waterloo, and Augsburg, we are organizing a school and conference &amp;ldquo;Frontiers at the intersection of quantum simulation and machine learning&amp;rdquo; to be held from Apr 8 to 19 2024 at the 

&lt;a href="https://www.ictp.it/" target="_blank">International Centre for Theoretical Physics&lt;/a> (ICTP) in Trieste. This will be the first event at ICTP co-sponsored by the 

&lt;a href="https://www.we-heraeus-stiftung.de/english/" target="_blank">WE Heraeus Foundation&lt;/a>. More detailed information will follow soon on the 

&lt;a href="https://indico.ictp.it/event/10466" target="_blank">event website&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Reconstructing effective Hamiltonians from nonequilibrium thermal and prethermal steady states</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/23_hamiltonian_reconstruction/</link><pubDate>Mon, 21 Aug 2023 09:06:28 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/23_hamiltonian_reconstruction/</guid><description>&lt;p>Reconstructing Hamiltonians from local measurements is key to enabling reliable quantum simulation: both validating the implemented model, and identifying any left-over terms with sufficient precision is a problem of increasing importance. Here we propose a deep-learning-assisted variational algorithm for Hamiltonian reconstruction by pre-processing a dataset that is diagnosed to contain thermal measurements of local operators. We demonstrate the efficient and precise reconstruction of local Hamiltonians, while long-range interacting Hamiltonians are reconstructed approximately. Away from equilibrium, for periodically and random multipolar driven systems, we reconstruct the effective Hamiltonian widely used for Floquet engineering of metastable steady states. Moreover, our approach allows us to reconstruct an effective quasilocal Hamiltonian even in the heating regime beyond the validity of the prethermal plateau, where perturbative expansions fail.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Jonas Rigo</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/people/jonas/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Aug 2023 09:50:51 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/people/jonas/</guid><description>&lt;p>Hi, I’m Jonas and currently I am a Postdoc in the Computational Quantum Science Research Group. I am interested in quantum many-body physics, ranging from condensed matter systems to quantum simulators. In my research I investigate modern machine learning methods that can potentially provide unprecedented insights into quantum many-body systems. In my free time I enjoy yoga, books and all possible ways to get up and down a mountain.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="short-cv">Short CV&lt;/h2>
&lt;table>
 &lt;thead>
 &lt;tr>
 &lt;th style="text-align: left">&lt;/th>
 &lt;th style="text-align: left">&lt;/th>
 &lt;/tr>
 &lt;/thead>
 &lt;tbody>
 &lt;tr>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">since 2023&lt;/td>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">&lt;em>Postdoc at 

&lt;a href="https://www.fz-juelich.de/de/pgi/pgi-8" target="_blank">FZ Jülich (PGI-8)&lt;/a>&lt;/em>&lt;/td>
 &lt;/tr>
 &lt;tr>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">2019-2023&lt;/td>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">&lt;em>PhD in physics at 

&lt;a href="https://www.ucd.ie/physics/" target="_blank">University College Dublin&lt;/a>&lt;/em>&lt;/td>
 &lt;/tr>
 &lt;tr>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">2013-2018&lt;/td>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">&lt;em>Bachelor and Master in physics at 

&lt;a href="https://www.uibk.ac.at/th-physik/index.html.de" target="_blank">University of Innsbruck&lt;/a>&lt;/em>&lt;/td>
 &lt;/tr>
 &lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table></description></item><item><title>Jonas joins us as a Postdoc</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/12-jonas-joined/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Aug 2023 09:47:15 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/12-jonas-joined/</guid><description>&lt;p>Our group keeps growing and today is 

&lt;a href="https://www.computational-quantum.science/people/jonas/">Jonas Rigo&lt;/a>&amp;rsquo;s first day as a Postdoc. Welcome, Jonas!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Simulating spectral functions with NQS</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/11-spectral-fun-published/</link><pubDate>Thu, 27 Jul 2023 16:56:49 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/11-spectral-fun-published/</guid><description>&lt;p>We developed a new approach to simulate spectral functions using neural quantum states, which for example accurately captures the gap closing at the phase transition of a two-dimensional quantum magnet despite the associated diverging time scale. The paper appeared today in 

&lt;a href="https://journals.aps.org/prl/abstract/10.1103/PhysRevLett.131.046501" target="_blank">Phys. Rev. Lett.&lt;/a>!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Mo graduated and continues to pursue a PhD</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/10-mo-joined/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2023 11:53:05 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/10-mo-joined/</guid><description>&lt;p>Last week, 

&lt;a href="https://www.computational-quantum.science/people/mo/">Mo Abedi&lt;/a> successfully defended his Master&amp;rsquo;s thesis and he will stay with us to pursue his PhD. In his research, he will continue to develop Reinforcement Learning approaches for optimal quantum control. Congratulations, Mo!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Francesca joined</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/9-francesca-joined/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 May 2023 11:53:05 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/9-francesca-joined/</guid><description>&lt;p>Today, 

&lt;a href="https://www.computational-quantum.science/people/francesca/">Francesca de Franco&lt;/a> joined our group as a new PhD student. She will explore how one can use near-term quantum devices to study many-body physics. Welcome Francesca!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Francesca de Franco</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/people/francesca/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 May 2023 11:36:10 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/people/francesca/</guid><description>&lt;p>Hi, I am Francesca!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>My research focuses on digital quantum simulations of quantum many-body systems. As a concrete example, I investigate the Floquet random circuit, a model used to study many-body localization. We employ variational methods to optimize the circuit for targeted quantum devices, reducing the circuit depth and enhancing their suitability for NISQ devices.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I am also interested in the dynamics of quantum many-body systems in non- equilibrium settings, such as the dynamics at first-order and continuous quan- tum transitions, whether they evolve unitarily or interact with environments.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="short-cv">Short CV&lt;/h2>
&lt;table>
 &lt;thead>
 &lt;tr>
 &lt;th style="text-align: left">&lt;/th>
 &lt;th style="text-align: left">&lt;/th>
 &lt;/tr>
 &lt;/thead>
 &lt;tbody>
 &lt;tr>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">since 2023&lt;/td>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">&lt;em>PhD student at 

&lt;a href="https://www.fz-juelich.de/de/pgi/pgi-8" target="_blank">FZ Jülich (PGI-8)&lt;/a> and 

&lt;a href="https://www.uni-regensburg.de/physik/fakultaet/startseite/index.html" target="_blank">University of Regensburg&lt;/a>&lt;/em>&lt;/td>
 &lt;/tr>
 &lt;tr>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">2020-2022&lt;/td>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">&lt;em>Master in Physics at the University of Pisa&lt;/em>&lt;/td>
 &lt;/tr>
 &lt;tr>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">2018-2020&lt;/td>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">&lt;em>Bachelor in Physics at the University of Calabria&lt;/em>&lt;/td>
 &lt;/tr>
 &lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table></description></item><item><title>Highly resolved spectral functions of two-dimensional systems with neural quantum states</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/22_spectral_fun/</link><pubDate>Thu, 16 Mar 2023 13:07:08 +0100</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/22_spectral_fun/</guid><description>We developed a new approach to simulate spectral functions using neural quantum states, which for example accurately captures the gap closing at the phase transition of a two-dimensional quantum magnet despite the associated diverging time scale.</description></item><item><title>Tutorial and Focus Session at DPG Spring Meeting</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/8-skm23/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2023 18:03:00 -0600</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/8-skm23/</guid><description>&lt;p>For ML+Quantum Physics enthusiasts and all those who would like to learn about it, we are organizing a Tutorial Session 

&lt;a href="https://www.dpg-verhandlungen.de/year/2023/conference/skm/part/tut/session/1" target="_blank">&amp;ldquo;Physics Meets Machine Learning&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a> and a Focus Session 

&lt;a href="https://www.dpg-verhandlungen.de/year/2023/conference/skm/part/dy/session/2" target="_blank">&amp;ldquo;Machine Learning for Complex Quantum Systems&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a> at the DPG Spring Meeting in Dresden. There will also be another Focus Session on 

&lt;a href="https://www.dpg-verhandlungen.de/year/2023/conference/skm/part/dy/session/11" target="_blank">&amp;ldquo;Understanding Machine Learning as Complex Interacting Systems&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a>. All these sessions promise to be very interesting with great invited speakers &amp;ndash; so come by!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Wave function network description and Kolmogorov complexity of quantum many-body systems</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/21_wave_function_nets/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 08:56:04 +0100</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/21_wave_function_nets/</guid><description>&lt;p>Programmable quantum devices are now able to probe wave functions at unprecedented levels. This is based on the ability to project the many-body state of atom and qubit arrays onto a measurement basis which produces snapshots of the system wave function. Extracting and processing information from such observations remains, however, an open quest. One often resorts to analyzing low-order correlation functions - i.e., discarding most of the available information content. Here, we introduce wave function networks - a mathematical framework to describe wave function snapshots based on network theory. For many-body systems, these networks can become scale free - a mathematical structure that has found tremendous success in a broad set of fields, ranging from biology to epidemics to internet science. We demonstrate the potential of applying these techniques to quantum science by introducing protocols to extract the Kolmogorov complexity corresponding to the output of a quantum simulator, and implementing tools for fully scalable cross-platform certification based on similarity tests between networks. We demonstrate the emergence of scale-free networks analyzing data from Rydberg quantum simulators manipulating up to 100 atoms. We illustrate how, upon crossing a phase transition, the system complexity decreases while correlation length increases - a direct signature of build up of universal behavior in data space. Comparing experiments with numerical simulations, we achieve cross-certification at the wave-function level up to timescales of 4 μ s with a confidence level of 90%, and determine experimental calibration intervals with unprecedented accuracy. Our framework is generically applicable to the output of quantum computers and simulators with in situ access to the system wave function, and requires probing accuracy and repetition rates accessible to most currently available platforms.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Optimizing Design Choices for Neural Quantum States</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/20_nqs_gs_architectures/</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2023 09:19:57 +0100</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/20_nqs_gs_architectures/</guid><description>&lt;p>Neural quantum states are a new family of variational ansätze for quantum-many body wave functions with advantageous properties in the notoriously challenging case of two spatial dimensions. Since their introduction a wide variety of different network architectures has been employed to study paradigmatic models in quantum many-body physics with a particular focus on quantum spin models. Nonetheless, many questions remain about the effect that the choice of architecture has on the performance on a given task. In this work, we present a unified comparison of a selection of popular network architectures and symmetrization schemes employed for ground state searches of prototypical spin Hamiltonians, namely the two-dimensional transverse-field Ising model and the J1-J2 model. In the presence of a non-trivial sign structure of the ground states, we find that the details of symmetrization crucially influence the performance. We describe this effect in detail and discuss its consequences, especially for autoregressive models, as their direct sampling procedure is not compatible with the symmetrization procedure that we found to be optimal.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>We're hiring!</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/7-hiring/</link><pubDate>Thu, 15 Dec 2022 11:37:19 +0100</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/7-hiring/</guid><description>&lt;p>Our group is expanding and we are currently looking to fill several Postdoc/PhD positions. One job ad is already 

&lt;a href="https://www.fz-juelich.de/en/careers/jobs/2022-417" target="_blank">posted on the FZJ job portal&lt;/a>. To learn about further opportunities, just 

&lt;a href="people/markus/">contact Markus&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Update&lt;/em>: All positions were filled in the meantime.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Qiskit Seminar on exploring the Jarzynski relation on a quantum computer</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/6-qiskit-seminar-jarzynski/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2022 10:53:07 +0100</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/6-qiskit-seminar-jarzynski/</guid><description>&lt;p>Last week, Dominik Hahn (MPI PKS) presented the outcomes of 

&lt;a href="publications/19_jarzynski">our collaboration on the quantum many-body Jarzynski equality&lt;/a> in the Qiskit Seminar Series. The recording is available 

&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UmYrTNQlvKw" target="_blank">on youtube&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Quantum ideas factory</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/5-qif-heidelberg/</link><pubDate>Sat, 29 Oct 2022 13:33:27 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/5-qif-heidelberg/</guid><description>&lt;p>During the next two days 

&lt;a href="https://www.computational-quantum.science/people/markus/">Markus&lt;/a> will mentor a team of talented students and young researchers, who will tackle the quantum control problem with reinforcement learning approaches at the scientific hackathon of the 

&lt;a href="http://www.efeqt.eu/index.php/quantum-ideas-factory/" target="_blank">Quantum Ideas Factory 2022&lt;/a> in Heidelberg. Thanks to 

&lt;a href="https://www.computational-quantum.science/people/mo/">Mo&lt;/a> for the help to set up the challenge. That&amp;rsquo;s going to be fun!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Lab course: Computational physics</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/teaching/lab_compphys_22/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2022 18:34:01 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/teaching/lab_compphys_22/</guid><description>&lt;p>This winter term (2022/23) we are launching this new branch of the Practical Course M at the University of Cologne. All information about the course can be found 

&lt;a href="http://www.thp.uni-koeln.de/trebst/PracticalCourse/index.html" target="_blank">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Discrete truncated Wigner approach to dynamical phase transitions in Ising models after a quantum quench</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/11_discrete_twa/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/11_discrete_twa/</guid><description>&lt;p>By means of the discrete truncated Wigner approximation we study dynamical phase transitions arising in the steady state of transverse-field Ising models after a quantum quench. Starting from a fully polarized ferromagnetic initial condition these transitions separate a phase with nonvanishing magnetization along the ordering direction from a symmetric phase upon increasing the transverse field. We consider two paradigmatic cases, a one-dimensional long-range model with power-law interactions \(\propto 1/r^\alpha\) decaying algebraically as a function of distance \(r\) and a two-dimensional system with short-range nearest-neighbour interactions. In the former case we identify dynamical phase transitions for \(\alpha\lesssim 2\) and we extract the critical exponents from a data collapse of the steady state magnetization for up to 1200 lattice sites. We find identical exponents for \(\alpha\lesssim 0.5\), suggesting that the dynamical transitions in this regime fall into the same universality class as the nonergodic mean-field limit. The two-dimensional Ising model is believed to be thermalizing, which we also confirm using exact diagonalization for small system sizes. Thus, the dynamical transition is expected to correspond to the thermal phase transition, which is consistent with our data upon comparing to equilibrium quantum Monte-Carlo simulations. We further test the accuracy of the discrete truncated Wigner approximation by comparing against numerically exact methods such as exact diagonalization, tensor network as well as artificial neural network states and we find good quantitative agreement on the accessible time scales. Finally, our work provides an additional contribution to the understanding of the range and the limitations of qualitative and quantitative applicability of the discrete truncated Wigner approximation.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Disorder-free localization in an interacting two-dimensional lattice gauge theory</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/10_disorder_free_localization/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/10_disorder_free_localization/</guid><description>&lt;p>Disorder-free localization has been recently introduced as a mechanism for ergodicity breaking in low-dimensional homogeneous lattice gauge theories caused by local constraints imposed by gauge invariance. We show that also genuinely interacting systems in two spatial dimensions can become nonergodic as a consequence of this mechanism. Specifically, we prove nonergodic behavior in the quantum link model by obtaining a rigorous bound on the localization-delocalization transition through a classical correlated percolation problem implying a fragmentation of Hilbert space on the nonergodic side of the transition. We study the quantum dynamics in this system by means of an efficient and perturbatively controlled representation of the wavefunction in terms of a variational network of classical spins akin to artificial neural networks. We identify a distinguishing dynamical signature by studying the propagation of line defects, yielding different light cone structures in the localized and ergodic phases, respectively. The methods we introduce in this work can be applied to any lattice gauge theory with finite-dimensional local Hilbert spaces irrespective of spatial dimensionality.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>From observations to complexity of quantum states via unsupervised learning</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/18_local_complexity/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/18_local_complexity/</guid><description>&lt;p>The vast complexity is a daunting property of generic quantum states that poses a significant challenge for theoretical treatment, especially in non-equilibrium setups. Therefore, it is vital to recognize states which are locally less complex and thus describable with (classical) effective theories. We use unsupervised learning with autoencoder neural networks to detect the local complexity of time-evolved states by determining the minimal number of parameters needed to reproduce local observations. The latter can be used as a probe of thermalization, to assign the local complexity of density matrices in open setups and for the reconstruction of underlying Hamiltonian operators. Our approach is an ideal diagnostics tool for data obtained from (noisy) quantum simulators because it requires only practically accessible local observations.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Irreversible dynamics in quantum many-body systems</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/6_irreversibility/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/6_irreversibility/</guid><description>&lt;p>Irreversibility, despite being a necessary condition for thermalization, still lacks a sound understanding in the context of isolated quantum many-body systems. In this work we approach this question by studying the behavior of generic many-body systems under imperfect effective time reversal, where the imperfection is introduced as a perturbation of the many-body state at the point of time reversal. Based on numerical simulations of the full quantum dynamics we demonstrate that observable echos occurring in this setting decay exponentially with a rate that is independent of the perturbation; hence, the sensitivity to perturbations is intrinsic to the system meaning that the dynamics is effectively irreversible.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>jVMC: Versatile and performant variational Monte Carlo leveraging automated differentiation and GPU acceleration</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/17_jvmc/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/17_jvmc/</guid><description>&lt;p>The introduction of Neural Quantum States (NQS) has recently given a new twist to variational Monte Carlo (VMC). The ability to systematically reduce the bias of the wave function ansatz renders the approach widely applicable. However, performant implementations are crucial to reach the numerical state of the art. Here, we present a Python codebase that supports arbitrary NQS architectures and model Hamiltonians. Additionally leveraging automatic differentiation, just-in-time compilation to accelerators, and distributed computing, it is designed to facilitate the composition of efficient NQS algorithms.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Learning the ground state of a non-stoquastic quantum Hamiltonian in a rugged neural network landscape</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/15_j1j2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/15_j1j2/</guid><description>&lt;p>Strongly interacting quantum systems described by non-stoquastic Hamiltonians exhibit rich low-temperature physics. Yet, their study poses a formidable challenge, even for state-of-the-art numerical techniques. Here, we investigate systematically the performance of a class of universal variational wave-functions based on artificial neural networks, by considering the frustrated spin-1/2 J1−J2 Heisenberg model on the square lattice. Focusing on neural network architectures without physics-informed input, we argue in favor of using an ansatz consisting of two decoupled real-valued networks, one for the amplitude and the other for the phase of the variational wavefunction. By introducing concrete mitigation strategies against inherent numerical instabilities in the stochastic reconfiguration algorithm we obtain a variational energy comparable to that reported recently with neural networks that incorporate knowledge about the physical system. Through a detailed analysis of the individual components of the algorithm, we conclude that the rugged nature of the energy landscape constitutes the major obstacle in finding a satisfactory approximation to the ground state wavefunction, and prevents learning the correct sign structure. In particular, we show that in the present setup the neural network expressivity and Monte Carlo sampling are not primary limiting factors.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Measuring complex partition function zeroes of Ising models in quantum simulators</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/8_fisher_zeros_qc/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/8_fisher_zeros_qc/</guid><description>&lt;p>Studying the zeroes of partition functions in the space of complex control parameters allows to understand formally how critical behavior of a many-body system can arise in the thermodynamic limit despite various no-go theorems for finite systems. In this work we propose protocols that can be realized in quantum simulators to measure the location of complex partition function zeroes of classical Ising models. The protocols are solely based on the implementation of simple two-qubit gates, local spin rotations, and projective measurements along two orthogonal quantization axes. Besides presenting numerical simulations of the measurement outcomes for an exemplary classical model, we discuss the effect of projection noise and the feasibility of the implementation on state of the art platforms for quantum simulation.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Quantum dynamics in transverse-field Ising models from classical networks</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/5_classical_nets/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/5_classical_nets/</guid><description>&lt;p>The efficient representation of quantum many-body states with classical resources is a key challenge in quantum many-body theory. In this work we analytically construct classical networks for the description of the quantum dynamics in transverse-field Ising models that can be solved efficiently using Monte Carlo techniques. Our perturbative construction encodes time-evolved quantum states of spin-1/2 systems in a network of classical spins with local couplings and can be directly generalized to other spin systems and higher spins. Using this construction we compute the transient dynamics in one, two, and three dimensions including local observables, entanglement production, and Loschmidt amplitudes using Monte Carlo algorithms and demonstrate the accuracy of this approach by comparisons to exact results. We include a mapping to equivalent artificial neural networks, which were recently introduced to provide a universal structure for classical network wave functions.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Quantum Many-Body Jarzynski Equality and Dissipative Noise on a Digital Quantum Computer</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/19_jarzynski/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/19_jarzynski/</guid><description>We explored fluctuations occuring in non-equilibrium processes implemented on a quantum processor, veryfying, for example, the Jarzynski equality in the regime of many interacting qubits.</description></item><item><title>Semiclassical echo dynamics in the Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev model</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/7_semiclassical_echoes/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/7_semiclassical_echoes/</guid><description>&lt;p>The existence of a quantum butterfly effect in the form of exponential sensitivity to small perturbations has been under debate for a long time. Lately, this question gained increased interest due to the proposal to probe chaotic dynamics and scrambling using out-of-time-order correlators. In this work we study echo dynamics in the Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev model under effective time reversal in a semiclassical approach. We demonstrate that small imperfections introduced in the time-reversal procedure result in an exponential divergence from the perfect echo, which allows to identify a Lyapunov exponent \( \lambda_L \). In particular, we find that \( \lambda_L \) is twice the Lyapunov exponent of the semiclassical equations of motion. This behavior is attributed to the growth of an out-of-time-order double commutator that resembles an out-of-time-order correlator.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Tripartite information, scrambling, and the role of Hilbert space partitioning in quantum lattice models</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/9_tripartite_info/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/9_tripartite_info/</guid><description>&lt;p>For the characterization of the dynamics in quantum many-body systems the question how information spreads and becomes distributed over the constituent degrees of freedom is of fundamental interest. The delocalization of information under many-body dynamics has been dubbed scrambling and out-of-time-order correlators were proposed to probe this behavior. In this work we investigate the time-evolution of tripartite information as a natural operator-independent measure of scrambling, which quantifies to which extent the initially localized information can only be recovered by global measurements. Studying the dynamics of quantum lattice models with tunable integrability breaking we demonstrate that in contrast to quadratic models generic interacting systems scramble information irrespective of the chosen partitioning of the Hilbert space, which justifies the characterization as scrambler. Without interactions the dynamics of tripartite information in momentum space reveals unambiguously the absence of scrambling.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Variational classical networks for dynamics in interacting quantum matter</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/13_vcn/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/13_vcn/</guid><description>&lt;p>Dynamics in correlated quantum matter is a hard problem, as its exact solution generally involves a computational effort that grows exponentially with the number of constituents. While a remarkable progress has been witnessed in recent years for one-dimensional systems, much less has been achieved for interacting quantum models in higher dimensions, since they incorporate an additional layer of complexity. In this work, we employ a variational method that allows for an efficient and controlled computation of the dynamics of quantum many-body systems in one and higher dimensions. The approach presented here introduces a variational class of wavefunctions based on complex networks of classical spins akin to artificial neural networks, which can be constructed in a controlled fashion. We provide a detailed prescription for such constructions and illustrate their performance by studying quantum quenches in one- and two-dimensional models. In particular, we investigate the nonequilibrium dynamics of a genuinely interacting two-dimensional lattice gauge theory, the quantum link model, for which we have recently shown &amp;ndash; employing the technique discussed thoroughly in this paper &amp;ndash; that it features disorder-free localization dynamics [P. Karpov et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 126, 130401 (2021)]. The present work not only supplies a framework to address purely theoretical questions but also could be used to provide a theoretical description of experiments in quantum simulators, which have recently seen an increased effort targeting two-dimensional geometries. Importantly, our method can be applied to any quantum many-body system with a well-defined classical limit.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Universal non-analytic behavior of the non-equilibrium Hall conductance in Floquet topological insulators</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/4_noneq_hall_2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 16:19:19 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/4_noneq_hall_2/</guid><description>&lt;p>We study the Hall conductance in a Floquet topological insulator in the long time limit after sudden switches of the driving amplitude. Based on a high frequency expansion of the effective Hamiltonian and the micromotion operator we demonstrate that the Hall conductance as function of the driving amplitude follows universal non-analytic laws close to phase transitions that are related to conic gap closing points, namely a logarithmic divergence for gapped initial states and jumps of a definite height for gapless initial states. This constitutes a generalization of the results known for the static systems to the driven case.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Universal nonanalytic behavior of the Hall conductance in a Chern insulator at the topologically driven nonequilibrium phase transition</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/3_noneq_hall_1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 16:16:15 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/3_noneq_hall_1/</guid><description>&lt;p>We study the Hall conductance of a Chern insulator after a global quench of the Hamiltonian. The Hall conductance in the long time limit is obtained by applying the linear response theory to the diagonal ensemble. It is expressed as the integral of the Berry curvature weighted by the occupation number over the Brillouin zone. We identify a topologically driven nonequilibrium phase transition, which is indicated by the nonanalyticity of the Hall conductance as a function of the energy gap m_f in the post-quench Hamiltonian H_f. The topological invariant for the quenched state is the winding number of the Green&amp;rsquo;s function W, which equals the Chern number for the ground state of H_f. In the limit that m_f goes to zero, the derivative of the Hall conductance with respect to m_f is proportional to ln(|m_f|), with the constant of proportionality being the ratio of the change of W at m_f = 0 to the energy gap in the initial state. This nonanalytic behavior is universal in two-band Chern insulators such as the Dirac model, the Haldane model, or the Kitaev honeycomb model in the fermionic basis.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Mo Abedi</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/people/mo/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2022 20:04:48 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/people/mo/</guid><description>&lt;p>Hi, I am Mo!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>My research interests lie at the crossroads between machine learning and quantum computing and quantum matter. I am currently writing my Masters thesis applying reinforcement learning for optimal quantum control. Aside from that, I am trying to do generative modelling and representation learning for learning quantum complexity.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Wladislaw Krinitsin</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/people/wladi/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2022 20:04:39 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/people/wladi/</guid><description>&lt;p>Hi, I am Wladi!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In my current research I am working on simulating non-equilibrium dynamics using machine learning and other techniques from many-body physics. Further topics I am interested in include non-abelian gauge theories, especially approaches to the low energy sector of QCD.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Markus Schmitt</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/people/markus/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2022 20:04:23 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/people/markus/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="short-cv">Short CV&lt;/h2>
&lt;table>
 &lt;thead>
 &lt;tr>
 &lt;th style="text-align: left">&lt;/th>
 &lt;th style="text-align: left">&lt;/th>
 &lt;/tr>
 &lt;/thead>
 &lt;tbody>
 &lt;tr>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">since 2023&lt;/td>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">&lt;em>Independent research group leader at 

&lt;a href="https://www.uni-regensburg.de/informatik-data-science/fakultaet/startseite/index.html" target="_blank">University of Regensburg&lt;/a>&lt;/em>&lt;/td>
 &lt;/tr>
 &lt;tr>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">since 2022&lt;/td>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">&lt;em>Junior group leader at 

&lt;a href="https://www.fz-juelich.de/de/pgi/pgi-8" target="_blank">FZ Jülich (PGI-8)&lt;/a>&lt;/em>&lt;/td>
 &lt;/tr>
 &lt;tr>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">2020-2022&lt;/td>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">&lt;em>Postdoc at 

&lt;a href="https://www.thp.uni-koeln.de" target="_blank">University of Cologne&lt;/a>&lt;/em>&lt;/td>
 &lt;/tr>
 &lt;tr>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">2018-2020&lt;/td>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">&lt;em>Postdoc at 

&lt;a href="https://cmt.berkeley.edu/" target="_blank">UC Berkeley&lt;/a> (

&lt;a href="https://www.leopoldina.org" target="_blank">Leopoldina Felloship&lt;/a>)&lt;/em>&lt;/td>
 &lt;/tr>
 &lt;tr>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">2018&lt;/td>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">&lt;em>Postdoc at 

&lt;a href="https://www.pks.mpg.de" target="_blank">MPI PKS&lt;/a>&lt;/em>&lt;/td>
 &lt;/tr>
 &lt;tr>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">2015-2018&lt;/td>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">&lt;em>PhD in Physics at the 

&lt;a href="https://www.theorie.physik.uni-goettingen.de" target="_blank">University of Göttingen&lt;/a>&lt;/em>&lt;/td>
 &lt;/tr>
 &lt;tr>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">2009-2014&lt;/td>
 &lt;td style="text-align: left">&lt;em>Studied physics and high performance computing in Göttingen and Edinburgh.&lt;/em>&lt;/td>
 &lt;/tr>
 &lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table></description></item><item><title>Effective time reversal and echo dynamics in the transverse field Ising model</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/2_ising_echo/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 14:40:01 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/2_ising_echo/</guid><description>&lt;p>The question of thermalisation in closed quantum many-body systems has received a lot of attention in the past few years. An intimately related question is whether a closed quantum system shows irreversible dynamics. However, irreversibility and what we actually mean by this in a quantum many-body system with unitary dynamics has been explored very little. In this work we investigate the dynamics of the Ising model in a transverse magnetic field involving an imperfect effective time reversal. We propose a definition of irreversibility based on the echo peak decay of observables. Inducing the effective time reversal by different protocols we find algebraic decay of the echo peak heights or an ever persisting echo peak indicating that the dynamics in this model is well reversible.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Dynamical Quantum Phase Transitions in the Kitaev Honeycomb Model</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/1_kitaev_dqpt/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 14:39:52 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/1_kitaev_dqpt/</guid><description>&lt;p>The notion of a dynamical quantum phase transition (DQPT) was recently introduced in [Heyl et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 110, 135704 (2013)] as the non-analytic behavior of the Loschmidt echo at critical times in the thermodynamic limit. In this work the quench dynamics in the ground state sector of the two-dimensional Kitaev honeycomb model are studied regarding the occurrence of DQPTs. For general two-dimensional systems of BCS-type it is demonstrated how the zeros of the Loschmidt echo coalesce to areas in the thermodynamic limit, implying that DQPTs occur as discontinuities in the second derivative. In the Kitaev honeycomb model DQPTs appear after quenches across a phase boundary or within the massless phase. In the 1d limit of the Kitaev honeycomb model it becomes clear that the discontinuity in the higher derivative is intimately related to the higher dimensionality of the non-degenerate model. Moreover, there is a strong connection between the stationary value of the rate function of the Loschmidt echo after long times and the occurrence of DQPTs in this model.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Complex quantum dynamics</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/research/nonequilibrium/</link><pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2022 20:40:06 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/research/nonequilibrium/</guid><description>RL is cool</description></item><item><title>Neural quantum states</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/research/neural_quantum_states/</link><pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2022 20:40:06 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/research/neural_quantum_states/</guid><description>NQS is cool</description></item><item><title>Reinforcement learning for quantum control</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/research/reinforcement_learning/</link><pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2022 20:40:06 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/research/reinforcement_learning/</guid><description>RL is cool</description></item><item><title>Quantum phase transition dynamics in the two-dimensional transverse-field Ising model</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/14_qkzm/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/14_qkzm/</guid><description>Based on simulations with tensor networks and neural quantum states we confirmed for the first time numerically the non-equilibrium scaling hypothesis of the Kibble-Zurek mechanism for a microscopic model system in two spatial dimensions.</description></item><item><title>Paper on quantum phase transition dynamics published</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/3-qkzm-published/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 14:54:44 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/3-qkzm-published/</guid><description>&lt;p>Our work on phase transition dynamics in the two-dimensional quantum Ising model appeared today in 

&lt;a href="https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/sciadv.abl6850" target="_blank">Science Advances&lt;/a>. Following up on it, an article for non-experts appeared on 

&lt;a href="https://www.pro-physik.de/nachrichten/kibble-zurek-mechanismus-gilt-auch-fuer-quanten-phasenuebergaenge" target="_blank">pro-physik.de&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Wladislaw Krinitsin joined</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/2-wladi-joined/</link><pubDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2022 09:00:00 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/2-wladi-joined/</guid><description>&lt;p>Today, 

&lt;a href="https://www.computational-quantum.science/people/wladi/">Wladislaw Krinitsin&lt;/a> joined our group as a new PhD student. He will work on neural quantum states for non-equilibrium dynamics. Welcome Wladi!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Helmholtz Young Investigator group started</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/1-hyig-started/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2022 19:24:14 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/1-hyig-started/</guid><description>&lt;p>Today, we are launching our Helmholtz Young Investigator Group &amp;ldquo;Machine Learning for Quantum Technology&amp;rdquo; at PGI-8 (FZ Jülich). Within this project we are going to develop machine learning techniques for the advancement of quantum technologies with a focus on two promising applications: On the one hand, we will employ 

&lt;a href="research/neural_quantum_states">neural quantum states&lt;/a> for simulations of non-equilibrium quantum matter, and, on the other hand, we will develop a versatile framework for 

&lt;a href="research/reinforcement_learning">optimal quantum control based on reinforcement learning&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Tutorial: Programmiertutorial für Computerphysik</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/teaching/lecture_compphys_22/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2022 18:23:25 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/teaching/lecture_compphys_22/</guid><description>&lt;p>As part of the lecture “Computational physics” we are teaching programming in Julia.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="materials">Materials&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Jupyter notebooks for the tutorial are available on 

&lt;a href="https://github.com/markusschmitt/compphys2022" target="_blank">GitHub&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>Time-dependent variational principle for open quantum systems with artificial neural networks</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/16_open_tdvp/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/16_open_tdvp/</guid><description>By generalizing the time-dependent variational principle to a purely probabilistic formulation of quantum mechanics we developed a new approach to simulate the time-evolution of open quantum many-body systems using, e.g., autoregressive neural networks.</description></item><item><title>Tutorial: Programmiertutorial für Computerphysik</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/teaching/lecture_compphys_21/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 18:23:25 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/teaching/lecture_compphys_21/</guid><description>&lt;p>As part of the lecture “Computational physics” we are teaching programming in Julia.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="materials">Materials&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Tutorial videos available on 

&lt;a href="https://vimeo.com/showcase/8384778" target="_blank">Vimeo&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Jupyter notebooks for the tutorial are available on 

&lt;a href="https://github.com/markusschmitt/compphys2021" target="_blank">GitHub&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>Seminar: Machine Learning Quantum Matter</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/teaching/seminar_mlqm_21/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 17:19:06 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/teaching/seminar_mlqm_21/</guid><description>&lt;p>The field of machine learning and artificial intelligence has flourished over the past years, fueled by a new generation of algorithms, ever growing resources of computational power, and the availability of “big data” in many fields. These technological advances have a strong impact also on the natural sciences — just recently, for example, the AlphaFold machine learning algorithm set new standards in the fundamentally difficult problem of protein folding. These developments have motivated researchers across all fields to explore machine learning techniques as an extension of their numerical toolbox.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this seminar, we will concentrate mostly on applications of machine learning (ML) in condensed matter physics. This is a perfect match: The core functionality of ML — pattern recognition and dimensional reduction— might be precisely what is needed to cure the “curse of dimensionality”, i.e. the exponential explosion of states in a Hilbert space, while, e.g., typical wavefunctions of quantum many-body systems are known to be “relatively simple”, occupying only a few important basis states. This suggests novel routes for data analysis and numerical simulation, but also inspires new conceptional developments. The talks will provide a basic introduction to various machine learning techniques by considering exemplary applications in condensed matter physics. A tentative list of topics is included below.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Quantum many-body dynamics in two dimensions with artificial neural networks</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/12_ann_dynamics/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Sep 2020 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/12_ann_dynamics/</guid><description>By developing a number of methodological advancements we demonstrated for the first time that neural quantum states are competitive with state-of-the-art tensor network techniques when simulating complex quantum dynamics in two spatial dimensions.</description></item></channel></rss>