<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>News on Computational Quantum Science</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/</link><description>Recent content in News on Computational Quantum Science</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2023 18:03:00 -0600</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Tutorial and Focus Session at DPG Spring Meeting</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/8-skm23/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2023 18:03:00 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/8-skm23/</guid><description>For ML+Quantum Physics enthusiasts and all those who would like to learn about it, we are organizing a Tutorial Session &amp;ldquo;Physics Meets Machine Learning&amp;rdquo; and a Focus Session &amp;ldquo;Machine Learning for Complex Quantum Systems&amp;rdquo; at the DPG Spring Meeting in Dresden. There will also be another Focus Session on &amp;ldquo;Understanding Machine Learning as Complex Interacting Systems&amp;rdquo;. All these sessions promise to be very interesting with great invited speakers &amp;ndash; so come by!</description></item><item><title>We're hiring!</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/7-hiring/</link><pubDate>Thu, 15 Dec 2022 11:37:19 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/7-hiring/</guid><description>Our group is expanding and we are currently looking to fill several Postdoc/PhD positions. One job ad is already posted on the FZJ job portal. To learn about further opportunities, just contact Markus.
Update: All positions were filled in the meantime.</description></item><item><title>Qiskit Seminar on exploring the Jarzynski relation on a quantum computer</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/6-qiskit-seminar-jarzynski/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2022 10:53:07 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/6-qiskit-seminar-jarzynski/</guid><description>Last week, Dominik Hahn (MPI PKS) presented the outcomes of our collaboration on the quantum many-body Jarzynski equality in the Qiskit Seminar Series. The recording is available on youtube.</description></item><item><title>Quantum ideas factory</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/5-qif-heidelberg/</link><pubDate>Sat, 29 Oct 2022 13:33:27 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/5-qif-heidelberg/</guid><description>During the next two days Markus will mentor a team of talented students and young researchers, who will tackle the quantum control problem with reinforcement learning approaches at the scientific hackathon of the Quantum Ideas Factory 2022 in Heidelberg. Thanks to Mo for the help to set up the challenge. That&amp;rsquo;s going to be fun!</description></item><item><title>Paper on quantum phase transition dynamics published</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/3-qkzm-published/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 14:54:44 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/3-qkzm-published/</guid><description>Our work on phase transition dynamics in the two-dimensional quantum Ising model appeared today in Science Advances. Following up on it, an article for non-experts appeared on pro-physik.de.</description></item><item><title>Wladislaw Krinitsin joined</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/2-wladi-joined/</link><pubDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2022 09:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/2-wladi-joined/</guid><description>Today, Wladislaw Krinitsin joined our group as a new PhD student. He will work on neural quantum states for non-equilibrium dynamics. Welcome Wladi!</description></item><item><title>Helmholtz Young Investigator group started</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/1-hyig-started/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2022 19:24:14 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/1-hyig-started/</guid><description>Today, we are launching our Helmholtz Young Investigator Group &amp;ldquo;Machine Learning for Quantum Technology&amp;rdquo; at PGI-8 (FZ Jülich). Within this project we are going to develop machine learning techniques for the advancement of quantum technologies with a focus on two promising applications: On the one hand, we will employ neural quantum states for simulations of non-equilibrium quantum matter, and, on the other hand, we will develop a versatile framework for optimal quantum control based on reinforcement learning.</description></item></channel></rss>