<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>News on Computational Quantum Science</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/</link><description>Recent content in News on Computational Quantum Science</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</managingEditor><webMaster>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 Jun 2024 14:09:43 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Jonas distinguished as Young Excellent Scientist</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/19-jonas-distinction/</link><pubDate>Wed, 26 Jun 2024 14:09:43 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/19-jonas-distinction/</guid><description>Our Postdoc Jonas has secured one of the five places in FZ Jülich&amp;rsquo;s Young Excellent Scientist Program (YESP). The program offers individual support modules, among which the funding to hold their own symposium on a topic of their choice. Congratulations, Jonas!</description></item><item><title>Opening for PhD position</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/18-phd-opening/</link><pubDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2024 19:00:34 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/18-phd-opening/</guid><description>We are looking for a new PhD student for a DFG-funded project on &amp;ldquo;machine learning to tailor correlated states of matter&amp;rdquo;. The project in cooperation with colleagues at MPI PKS will evolve around neural quantum states for non-equilibrium quantum many-body physics.
Update: The position has been filled.</description></item><item><title>Introducing wave function networks</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/17-wfn-published/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Jun 2024 14:19:31 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/17-wfn-published/</guid><description>The advent of quantum simulators and computers has made projective measurement a reality at the many-particle level: Experiments routinely collect high-quality pictures of wave functions made of hundreds of components. But the wealth of information obtained challenges traditional theoretical modeling, which often focuses on a few observables. In our work, that is now published in Phys. Rev. X, we introduce a framework to describe wave-function measurements using network theory, enabling the discovery of a very deep inner structure in quantum wave functions: scale-freeness similar to other completely disconnected ensembles, such as those found in communication, social networks and the internet.</description></item><item><title>Opening for student assistant</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/16-shk-opening/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 May 2024 11:15:17 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/16-shk-opening/</guid><description>We are lookging for a dedicated student assistant to support our research team. The main tasks will evolve around programming and conducting explorative studies in the area of machine learning for quantum science.
https://doi.org/10.1088/2632-2153/ad4f4d</description></item><item><title>Learning Hamiltonians that describe non-equilibrium steady states</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/15-floquet-learning-published/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2024 17:45:40 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/15-floquet-learning-published/</guid><description>Periodic driving is a prime way to engineer quantum matter with interesting properties. For this purpose, it is essential to bring the system into metastable steady states, the properties of which governed by a corresponding effective Hamiltonian. We have developed a deep-learning-assisted variational algorithm to reconstruct such effective Hamiltonians from observations. Thereby, we could recover local Hamiltonians in pre-thermal regimes and observe the growing complexity of instantaneous effective Hamiltonians in subsequent heating regimes. Our findings are now published in Phys. Rev. Research.</description></item><item><title>Observing fluctuation relations on a quantum processor</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/14-jarzynski-published/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Nov 2023 09:46:09 +0100</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/14-jarzynski-published/</guid><description>Jarzynski’s equality describes a relation in statistical physics between the fluctuations during a work process and the thermal free energy difference corresponding to the initial and final ensemble. While Jarzynski’s equality has been checked in many scenarios, previous experiments focused on systems with only a handful of degrees of freedom in the quantum regime. In our collaboration with colleagues at MPI PKS, the University of Bonn, and UC Berkeley/LBNL, we probed for the first time Jarzynski’s equality in the quantum many-body regime. We devise a dynamical protocol to measure work on quantum computers using a suitably prepared thermal ensemble and tested Jarzynski&amp;rsquo;s equality on different quantum processors with up to 16 qubits. The article has now been published in Phys. Rev.</description></item><item><title>Combined school and conference at ICTP</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/13-ictp-conference/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Oct 2023 09:33:01 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/13-ictp-conference/</guid><description>Together with colleagues from Hamburg, Waterloo, and Augsburg, we are organizing a school and conference &amp;ldquo;Frontiers at the intersection of quantum simulation and machine learning&amp;rdquo; to be held from Apr 8 to 19 2024 at the International Centre for Theoretical Physics (ICTP) in Trieste. This will be the first event at ICTP co-sponsored by the WE Heraeus Foundation. More detailed information will follow soon on the event website.</description></item><item><title>Jonas joins us as a Postdoc</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/12-jonas-joined/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Aug 2023 09:47:15 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/12-jonas-joined/</guid><description>Our group keeps growing and today is Jonas Rigo&amp;rsquo;s first day as a Postdoc. Welcome, Jonas!</description></item><item><title>Simulating spectral functions with NQS</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/11-spectral-fun-published/</link><pubDate>Thu, 27 Jul 2023 16:56:49 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/11-spectral-fun-published/</guid><description>We developed a new approach to simulate spectral functions using neural quantum states, which for example accurately captures the gap closing at the phase transition of a two-dimensional quantum magnet despite the associated diverging time scale. The paper appeared today in Phys. Rev. Lett.!</description></item><item><title>Mo graduated and continues to pursue a PhD</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/10-mo-joined/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2023 11:53:05 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/10-mo-joined/</guid><description>Last week, Mo Abedi successfully defended his Master&amp;rsquo;s thesis and he will stay with us to pursue his PhD. In his research, he will continue to develop Reinforcement Learning approaches for optimal quantum control. Congratulations, Mo!</description></item><item><title>Francesca joined</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/9-francesca-joined/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 May 2023 11:53:05 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/9-francesca-joined/</guid><description>Today, Francesca de Franco joined our group as a new PhD student. She will explore how one can use near-term quantum devices to study many-body physics. Welcome Francesca!</description></item><item><title>Tutorial and Focus Session at DPG Spring Meeting</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/8-skm23/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2023 18:03:00 -0600</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/8-skm23/</guid><description>For ML+Quantum Physics enthusiasts and all those who would like to learn about it, we are organizing a Tutorial Session &amp;ldquo;Physics Meets Machine Learning&amp;rdquo; and a Focus Session &amp;ldquo;Machine Learning for Complex Quantum Systems&amp;rdquo; at the DPG Spring Meeting in Dresden. There will also be another Focus Session on &amp;ldquo;Understanding Machine Learning as Complex Interacting Systems&amp;rdquo;. All these sessions promise to be very interesting with great invited speakers &amp;ndash; so come by!</description></item><item><title>We're hiring!</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/7-hiring/</link><pubDate>Thu, 15 Dec 2022 11:37:19 +0100</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/7-hiring/</guid><description>Our group is expanding and we are currently looking to fill several Postdoc/PhD positions. One job ad is already posted on the FZJ job portal. To learn about further opportunities, just contact Markus.
Update: All positions were filled in the meantime.</description></item><item><title>Qiskit Seminar on exploring the Jarzynski relation on a quantum computer</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/6-qiskit-seminar-jarzynski/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2022 10:53:07 +0100</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/6-qiskit-seminar-jarzynski/</guid><description>Last week, Dominik Hahn (MPI PKS) presented the outcomes of our collaboration on the quantum many-body Jarzynski equality in the Qiskit Seminar Series. The recording is available on youtube.</description></item><item><title>Quantum ideas factory</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/5-qif-heidelberg/</link><pubDate>Sat, 29 Oct 2022 13:33:27 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/5-qif-heidelberg/</guid><description>During the next two days Markus will mentor a team of talented students and young researchers, who will tackle the quantum control problem with reinforcement learning approaches at the scientific hackathon of the Quantum Ideas Factory 2022 in Heidelberg. Thanks to Mo for the help to set up the challenge. That&amp;rsquo;s going to be fun!</description></item><item><title>Paper on quantum phase transition dynamics published</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/3-qkzm-published/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 14:54:44 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/3-qkzm-published/</guid><description>Our work on phase transition dynamics in the two-dimensional quantum Ising model appeared today in Science Advances. Following up on it, an article for non-experts appeared on pro-physik.de.</description></item><item><title>Wladislaw Krinitsin joined</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/2-wladi-joined/</link><pubDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2022 09:00:00 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/2-wladi-joined/</guid><description>Today, Wladislaw Krinitsin joined our group as a new PhD student. He will work on neural quantum states for non-equilibrium dynamics. Welcome Wladi!</description></item><item><title>Helmholtz Young Investigator group started</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/1-hyig-started/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2022 19:24:14 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/news/1-hyig-started/</guid><description>Today, we are launching our Helmholtz Young Investigator Group &amp;ldquo;Machine Learning for Quantum Technology&amp;rdquo; at PGI-8 (FZ Jülich). Within this project we are going to develop machine learning techniques for the advancement of quantum technologies with a focus on two promising applications: On the one hand, we will employ neural quantum states for simulations of non-equilibrium quantum matter, and, on the other hand, we will develop a versatile framework for optimal quantum control based on reinforcement learning.</description></item></channel></rss>