<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>People on Computational Quantum Science</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/people/</link><description>Recent content in People on Computational Quantum Science</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</managingEditor><webMaster>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Aug 2023 09:50:51 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.computational-quantum.science/people/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Jonas Rigo</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/people/jonas/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Aug 2023 09:50:51 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/people/jonas/</guid><description>Hi, I’m Jonas and currently I am a Postdoc in the Computational Quantum Science Research Group. I am interested in quantum many-body physics, ranging from condensed matter systems to quantum simulators. In my research I investigate modern machine learning methods that can potentially provide unprecedented insights into quantum many-body systems. In my free time I enjoy yoga, books and all possible ways to get up and down a mountain.
Short CV since 2023 Postdoc at FZ Jülich (PGI-8) 2019-2023 PhD in physics at University College Dublin 2013-2018 Bachelor and Master in physics at University of Innsbruck</description></item><item><title>Francesca de Franco</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/people/francesca/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 May 2023 11:36:10 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/people/francesca/</guid><description>Hi, I am Francesca!
My research focuses on digital quantum simulations of quantum many-body systems. As a concrete example, I investigate the Floquet random circuit, a model used to study many-body localization. We employ variational methods to optimize the circuit for targeted quantum devices, reducing the circuit depth and enhancing their suitability for NISQ devices.
I am also interested in the dynamics of quantum many-body systems in non- equilibrium settings, such as the dynamics at first-order and continuous quan- tum transitions, whether they evolve unitarily or interact with environments.
Short CV since 2023 PhD student at FZ Jülich (PGI-8) and University of Regensburg 2020-2022 Master in Physics at the University of Pisa 2018-2020 Bachelor in Physics at the University of Calabria</description></item><item><title>Mo Abedi</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/people/mo/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2022 20:04:48 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/people/mo/</guid><description>Hi, I am Mo!
My research interests lie at the crossroads between machine learning and quantum computing and quantum matter. I am currently writing my Masters thesis applying reinforcement learning for optimal quantum control. Aside from that, I am trying to do generative modelling and representation learning for learning quantum complexity.</description></item><item><title>Wladislaw Krinitsin</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/people/wladi/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2022 20:04:39 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/people/wladi/</guid><description>Hi, I am Wladi!
In my current research I am working on simulating non-equilibrium dynamics using machine learning and other techniques from many-body physics. Further topics I am interested in include non-abelian gauge theories, especially approaches to the low energy sector of QCD.</description></item><item><title>Markus Schmitt</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/people/markus/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2022 20:04:23 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/people/markus/</guid><description>Short CV since 2023 Independent research group leader at University of Regensburg since 2022 Junior group leader at FZ Jülich (PGI-8) 2020-2022 Postdoc at University of Cologne 2018-2020 Postdoc at UC Berkeley ( Leopoldina Felloship) 2018 Postdoc at MPI PKS 2015-2018 PhD in Physics at the University of Göttingen 2009-2014 Studied physics and high performance computing in Göttingen and Edinburgh.</description></item></channel></rss>