<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Teachings on Computational Quantum Science</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/teaching/</link><description>Recent content in Teachings on Computational Quantum Science</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</managingEditor><webMaster>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2024 21:21:34 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.computational-quantum.science/teaching/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Physics meets information</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/teaching/24_physics_meets_info/</link><pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2024 21:21:34 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/teaching/24_physics_meets_info/</guid><description>Many-body physics and information theory share a rich interface with intriguing connections. First of all, any information has to be carried by physical objects and - accordingly - information processing has to follow the laws of physics. Moreover, the concept of information can itself become part of physical processes, leading to the conclusion that &amp;ldquo;information is physical&amp;rdquo;. From this perspective, the course will cover the following topics:
Entropy and the 2nd law of thermodynamics Information theory Thermodynamics: Maxwell demon and Landauer principle Statistical mechanics: Jaynes&amp;rsquo; principle and renormalization group Quantum information Materials SPUR Course materials in GRIPS</description></item><item><title>Lab course: Computational physics</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/teaching/lab_compphys_22/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2022 18:34:01 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/teaching/lab_compphys_22/</guid><description>This winter term (2022/23) we are launching this new branch of the Practical Course M at the University of Cologne. All information about the course can be found here.</description></item><item><title>Tutorial: Programmiertutorial für Computerphysik</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/teaching/lecture_compphys_22/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2022 18:23:25 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/teaching/lecture_compphys_22/</guid><description>As part of the lecture “Computational physics” we are teaching programming in Julia.
Materials Jupyter notebooks for the tutorial are available on GitHub.</description></item><item><title>Tutorial: Programmiertutorial für Computerphysik</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/teaching/lecture_compphys_21/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 18:23:25 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/teaching/lecture_compphys_21/</guid><description>As part of the lecture “Computational physics” we are teaching programming in Julia.
Materials Tutorial videos available on Vimeo. Jupyter notebooks for the tutorial are available on GitHub.</description></item><item><title>Seminar: Machine Learning Quantum Matter</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/teaching/seminar_mlqm_21/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 17:19:06 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/teaching/seminar_mlqm_21/</guid><description>The field of machine learning and artificial intelligence has flourished over the past years, fueled by a new generation of algorithms, ever growing resources of computational power, and the availability of “big data” in many fields. These technological advances have a strong impact also on the natural sciences — just recently, for example, the AlphaFold machine learning algorithm set new standards in the fundamentally difficult problem of protein folding. These developments have motivated researchers across all fields to explore machine learning techniques as an extension of their numerical toolbox.
In this seminar, we will concentrate mostly on applications of machine learning (ML) in condensed matter physics. This is a perfect match: The core functionality of ML — pattern recognition and dimensional reduction— might be precisely what is needed to cure the “curse of dimensionality”, i.</description></item></channel></rss>