<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>NQS on Computational Quantum Science</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/tags/nqs/</link><description>Recent content in NQS on Computational Quantum Science</description><generator>Hugo 0.125.0</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</managingEditor><webMaster>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2023 09:19:57 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.computational-quantum.science/tags/nqs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Optimizing Design Choices for Neural Quantum States</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/20_nqs_gs_architectures/</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2023 09:19:57 +0100</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/20_nqs_gs_architectures/</guid><description>Neural quantum states are a new family of variational ansätze for quantum-many body wave functions with advantageous properties in the notoriously challenging case of two spatial dimensions. Since their introduction a wide variety of different network architectures has been employed to study paradigmatic models in quantum many-body physics with a particular focus on quantum spin models. Nonetheless, many questions remain about the effect that the choice of architecture has on the performance on a given task. In this work, we present a unified comparison of a selection of popular network architectures and symmetrization schemes employed for ground state searches of prototypical spin Hamiltonians, namely the two-dimensional transverse-field Ising model and the J1-J2 model. In the presence of a non-trivial sign structure of the ground states, we find that the details of symmetrization crucially influence the performance.</description></item></channel></rss>