<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Computational Quantum Science</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/joinus/jobs/</link><description>Recent content on Computational Quantum Science</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</managingEditor><webMaster>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2024 13:28:07 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.computational-quantum.science/joinus/jobs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>PhD position: Neural quantum states for non-equilibrium quantum many-body physics</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/joinus/jobs/2024-phd/</link><pubDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2024 13:28:07 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/joinus/jobs/2024-phd/</guid><description>The research of our &amp;ldquo;Computational quantum science&amp;rdquo; research group is directed at understanding and controlling the collective dynamics of quantum many-body systems far from equilibrium, which may ultimately pave the way to devise new technologies that rely on the quantum laws of nature. For investigations based on microscopic model systems one has to devise strategies to deal with the curse of dimensionality inherent to the quantum many-body problem. Particularly challenging is the development of efficient and versatile computational methods that serve as crucial link between experimental observations and theoretical models. For this purpose, we employ machine learning methods, which are for example well suited to represent the many-body wave function in a compressed form.
Our group is based at the University of Regensburg and furthermore affiliated with PGI-8 at Forschungszentrum Jülich.</description></item><item><title>Student assistant in machine learning for quantum science</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/joinus/jobs/2024-shk/</link><pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2024 18:28:07 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/joinus/jobs/2024-shk/</guid><description>We are currently lookging for a dedicated student assistant to support our research team. The main tasks will evolve around programming and conducting explorative studies in the area of machine learning for quantum science.
Requirements:
Solid programming skills in Python or Julia Basic knowledge of quantum mechanics and statistical physics Ideally, basic knowledge of machine learning, especially artificial neural networks Interest in learning more about the topics above Ability to work independently Motivation to work in an international research team Enrollment at the University of Regensburg How to apply:
If you are interested in this position, don&amp;rsquo;t hesitate to contact Markus via e-mail. Please attach a current transcript of records and briefly sketch how you match the opening.</description></item></channel></rss>