<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Publications on Computational Quantum Science</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/</link><description>Recent content in Publications on Computational Quantum Science</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Mar 2023 13:07:08 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Highly resolved spectral functions of two-dimensional systems with neural quantum states</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/22_spectral_fun/</link><pubDate>Thu, 16 Mar 2023 13:07:08 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/22_spectral_fun/</guid><description>Spectral functions are central to link experimental probes to theoretical models in condensed matter physics. However, performing exact numerical calculations for interacting quantum matter has remained a key challenge especially beyond one spatial dimension. In this work, we develop a versatile and numerically exact approach using neural quantum states to obtain spectral properties based on simulations of the dynamics of excitations initially localized in real or momentum space. We apply this approach to compute the dynamical structure factor in the vicinity of phase transitions of different two-dimensional quantum Ising models, including one that describes the complex density wave orders of Rydberg atom arrays. When combined with deep network architectures we find that our method reliably describes dynamical structure factors of arrays with up to 24×24 spins, including the diverging time scales at critical points.</description></item><item><title>Wave function network description and Kolmogorov complexity of quantum many-body systems</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/21_wave_function_nets/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 08:56:04 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/21_wave_function_nets/</guid><description>Programmable quantum devices are now able to probe wave functions at unprecedented levels. This is based on the ability to project the many-body state of atom and qubit arrays onto a measurement basis which produces snapshots of the system wave function. Extracting and processing information from such observations remains, however, an open quest. One often resorts to analyzing low-order correlation functions - i.e., discarding most of the available information content. Here, we introduce wave function networks - a mathematical framework to describe wave function snapshots based on network theory. For many-body systems, these networks can become scale free - a mathematical structure that has found tremendous success in a broad set of fields, ranging from biology to epidemics to internet science.</description></item><item><title>Optimizing Design Choices for Neural Quantum States</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/20_nqs_gs_architectures/</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2023 09:19:57 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/20_nqs_gs_architectures/</guid><description>Neural quantum states are a new family of variational ansätze for quantum-many body wave functions with advantageous properties in the notoriously challenging case of two spatial dimensions. Since their introduction a wide variety of different network architectures has been employed to study paradigmatic models in quantum many-body physics with a particular focus on quantum spin models. Nonetheless, many questions remain about the effect that the choice of architecture has on the performance on a given task. In this work, we present a unified comparison of a selection of popular network architectures and symmetrization schemes employed for ground state searches of prototypical spin Hamiltonians, namely the two-dimensional transverse-field Ising model and the J1-J2 model. In the presence of a non-trivial sign structure of the ground states, we find that the details of symmetrization crucially influence the performance.</description></item><item><title>Discrete truncated Wigner approach to dynamical phase transitions in Ising models after a quantum quench</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/11_discrete_twa/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/11_discrete_twa/</guid><description>By means of the discrete truncated Wigner approximation we study dynamical phase transitions arising in the steady state of transverse-field Ising models after a quantum quench. Starting from a fully polarized ferromagnetic initial condition these transitions separate a phase with nonvanishing magnetization along the ordering direction from a symmetric phase upon increasing the transverse field. We consider two paradigmatic cases, a one-dimensional long-range model with power-law interactions \(\propto 1/r^\alpha\) decaying algebraically as a function of distance \(r\) and a two-dimensional system with short-range nearest-neighbour interactions. In the former case we identify dynamical phase transitions for \(\alpha\lesssim 2\) and we extract the critical exponents from a data collapse of the steady state magnetization for up to 1200 lattice sites. We find identical exponents for \(\alpha\lesssim 0.</description></item><item><title>Disorder-free localization in an interacting two-dimensional lattice gauge theory</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/10_disorder_free_localization/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/10_disorder_free_localization/</guid><description>Disorder-free localization has been recently introduced as a mechanism for ergodicity breaking in low-dimensional homogeneous lattice gauge theories caused by local constraints imposed by gauge invariance. We show that also genuinely interacting systems in two spatial dimensions can become nonergodic as a consequence of this mechanism. Specifically, we prove nonergodic behavior in the quantum link model by obtaining a rigorous bound on the localization-delocalization transition through a classical correlated percolation problem implying a fragmentation of Hilbert space on the nonergodic side of the transition. We study the quantum dynamics in this system by means of an efficient and perturbatively controlled representation of the wavefunction in terms of a variational network of classical spins akin to artificial neural networks. We identify a distinguishing dynamical signature by studying the propagation of line defects, yielding different light cone structures in the localized and ergodic phases, respectively.</description></item><item><title>From observations to complexity of quantum states via unsupervised learning</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/18_local_complexity/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/18_local_complexity/</guid><description>The vast complexity is a daunting property of generic quantum states that poses a significant challenge for theoretical treatment, especially in non-equilibrium setups. Therefore, it is vital to recognize states which are locally less complex and thus describable with (classical) effective theories. We use unsupervised learning with autoencoder neural networks to detect the local complexity of time-evolved states by determining the minimal number of parameters needed to reproduce local observations. The latter can be used as a probe of thermalization, to assign the local complexity of density matrices in open setups and for the reconstruction of underlying Hamiltonian operators. Our approach is an ideal diagnostics tool for data obtained from (noisy) quantum simulators because it requires only practically accessible local observations.</description></item><item><title>Irreversible dynamics in quantum many-body systems</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/6_irreversibility/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/6_irreversibility/</guid><description>Irreversibility, despite being a necessary condition for thermalization, still lacks a sound understanding in the context of isolated quantum many-body systems. In this work we approach this question by studying the behavior of generic many-body systems under imperfect effective time reversal, where the imperfection is introduced as a perturbation of the many-body state at the point of time reversal. Based on numerical simulations of the full quantum dynamics we demonstrate that observable echos occurring in this setting decay exponentially with a rate that is independent of the perturbation; hence, the sensitivity to perturbations is intrinsic to the system meaning that the dynamics is effectively irreversible.</description></item><item><title>jVMC: Versatile and performant variational Monte Carlo leveraging automated differentiation and GPU acceleration</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/17_jvmc/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/17_jvmc/</guid><description>The introduction of Neural Quantum States (NQS) has recently given a new twist to variational Monte Carlo (VMC). The ability to systematically reduce the bias of the wave function ansatz renders the approach widely applicable. However, performant implementations are crucial to reach the numerical state of the art. Here, we present a Python codebase that supports arbitrary NQS architectures and model Hamiltonians. Additionally leveraging automatic differentiation, just-in-time compilation to accelerators, and distributed computing, it is designed to facilitate the composition of efficient NQS algorithms.</description></item><item><title>Learning the ground state of a non-stoquastic quantum Hamiltonian in a rugged neural network landscape</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/15_j1j2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/15_j1j2/</guid><description>Strongly interacting quantum systems described by non-stoquastic Hamiltonians exhibit rich low-temperature physics. Yet, their study poses a formidable challenge, even for state-of-the-art numerical techniques. Here, we investigate systematically the performance of a class of universal variational wave-functions based on artificial neural networks, by considering the frustrated spin-1/2 J1−J2 Heisenberg model on the square lattice. Focusing on neural network architectures without physics-informed input, we argue in favor of using an ansatz consisting of two decoupled real-valued networks, one for the amplitude and the other for the phase of the variational wavefunction. By introducing concrete mitigation strategies against inherent numerical instabilities in the stochastic reconfiguration algorithm we obtain a variational energy comparable to that reported recently with neural networks that incorporate knowledge about the physical system.</description></item><item><title>Measuring complex partition function zeroes of Ising models in quantum simulators</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/8_fisher_zeros_qc/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/8_fisher_zeros_qc/</guid><description>Studying the zeroes of partition functions in the space of complex control parameters allows to understand formally how critical behavior of a many-body system can arise in the thermodynamic limit despite various no-go theorems for finite systems. In this work we propose protocols that can be realized in quantum simulators to measure the location of complex partition function zeroes of classical Ising models. The protocols are solely based on the implementation of simple two-qubit gates, local spin rotations, and projective measurements along two orthogonal quantization axes. Besides presenting numerical simulations of the measurement outcomes for an exemplary classical model, we discuss the effect of projection noise and the feasibility of the implementation on state of the art platforms for quantum simulation.</description></item><item><title>Quantum dynamics in transverse-field Ising models from classical networks</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/5_classical_nets/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/5_classical_nets/</guid><description>The efficient representation of quantum many-body states with classical resources is a key challenge in quantum many-body theory. In this work we analytically construct classical networks for the description of the quantum dynamics in transverse-field Ising models that can be solved efficiently using Monte Carlo techniques. Our perturbative construction encodes time-evolved quantum states of spin-1/2 systems in a network of classical spins with local couplings and can be directly generalized to other spin systems and higher spins. Using this construction we compute the transient dynamics in one, two, and three dimensions including local observables, entanglement production, and Loschmidt amplitudes using Monte Carlo algorithms and demonstrate the accuracy of this approach by comparisons to exact results. We include a mapping to equivalent artificial neural networks, which were recently introduced to provide a universal structure for classical network wave functions.</description></item><item><title>Semiclassical echo dynamics in the Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev model</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/7_semiclassical_echoes/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/7_semiclassical_echoes/</guid><description>The existence of a quantum butterfly effect in the form of exponential sensitivity to small perturbations has been under debate for a long time. Lately, this question gained increased interest due to the proposal to probe chaotic dynamics and scrambling using out-of-time-order correlators. In this work we study echo dynamics in the Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev model under effective time reversal in a semiclassical approach. We demonstrate that small imperfections introduced in the time-reversal procedure result in an exponential divergence from the perfect echo, which allows to identify a Lyapunov exponent \( \lambda_L \). In particular, we find that \( \lambda_L \) is twice the Lyapunov exponent of the semiclassical equations of motion. This behavior is attributed to the growth of an out-of-time-order double commutator that resembles an out-of-time-order correlator.</description></item><item><title>Tripartite information, scrambling, and the role of Hilbert space partitioning in quantum lattice models</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/9_tripartite_info/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/9_tripartite_info/</guid><description>For the characterization of the dynamics in quantum many-body systems the question how information spreads and becomes distributed over the constituent degrees of freedom is of fundamental interest. The delocalization of information under many-body dynamics has been dubbed scrambling and out-of-time-order correlators were proposed to probe this behavior. In this work we investigate the time-evolution of tripartite information as a natural operator-independent measure of scrambling, which quantifies to which extent the initially localized information can only be recovered by global measurements. Studying the dynamics of quantum lattice models with tunable integrability breaking we demonstrate that in contrast to quadratic models generic interacting systems scramble information irrespective of the chosen partitioning of the Hilbert space, which justifies the characterization as scrambler. Without interactions the dynamics of tripartite information in momentum space reveals unambiguously the absence of scrambling.</description></item><item><title>Variational classical networks for dynamics in interacting quantum matter</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/13_vcn/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/13_vcn/</guid><description>Dynamics in correlated quantum matter is a hard problem, as its exact solution generally involves a computational effort that grows exponentially with the number of constituents. While a remarkable progress has been witnessed in recent years for one-dimensional systems, much less has been achieved for interacting quantum models in higher dimensions, since they incorporate an additional layer of complexity. In this work, we employ a variational method that allows for an efficient and controlled computation of the dynamics of quantum many-body systems in one and higher dimensions. The approach presented here introduces a variational class of wavefunctions based on complex networks of classical spins akin to artificial neural networks, which can be constructed in a controlled fashion. We provide a detailed prescription for such constructions and illustrate their performance by studying quantum quenches in one- and two-dimensional models.</description></item><item><title>Verification of the Quantum Jarzynski Equality on Digital Quantum Computers</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/19_jarzynski/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/19_jarzynski/</guid><description>The quantum Jarzynski equality and the Crooks relation are fundamental laws connecting equilibrium processes with nonequilibrium fluctuations. While they are well established theoretically and also experimental realizations for simple few-body systems already exist, a verification in the quantum many-body regime is still missing. Here, we present results for nonequilibrium protocols in systems with up to sixteen interacting degrees of freedom obtained on trapped ion and superconducting qubit quantum computers, which verify the quantum Jarzynski equality and the Crooks relation in the many-body regime. To achieve this, we overcome present-day limitations in the preparation of thermal ensembles and in the measurement of work distributions on noisy intermediate-scale quantum devices. We discuss the accuracy to which the Jarzynski equality holds on different quantum computing platforms subject to platform-specific errors.</description></item><item><title>Universal non-analytic behavior of the non-equilibrium Hall conductance in Floquet topological insulators</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/4_noneq_hall_2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 16:19:19 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/4_noneq_hall_2/</guid><description>We study the Hall conductance in a Floquet topological insulator in the long time limit after sudden switches of the driving amplitude. Based on a high frequency expansion of the effective Hamiltonian and the micromotion operator we demonstrate that the Hall conductance as function of the driving amplitude follows universal non-analytic laws close to phase transitions that are related to conic gap closing points, namely a logarithmic divergence for gapped initial states and jumps of a definite height for gapless initial states. This constitutes a generalization of the results known for the static systems to the driven case.</description></item><item><title>Universal nonanalytic behavior of the Hall conductance in a Chern insulator at the topologically driven nonequilibrium phase transition</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/3_noneq_hall_1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 16:16:15 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/3_noneq_hall_1/</guid><description>We study the Hall conductance of a Chern insulator after a global quench of the Hamiltonian. The Hall conductance in the long time limit is obtained by applying the linear response theory to the diagonal ensemble. It is expressed as the integral of the Berry curvature weighted by the occupation number over the Brillouin zone. We identify a topologically driven nonequilibrium phase transition, which is indicated by the nonanalyticity of the Hall conductance as a function of the energy gap m_f in the post-quench Hamiltonian H_f. The topological invariant for the quenched state is the winding number of the Green&amp;rsquo;s function W, which equals the Chern number for the ground state of H_f. In the limit that m_f goes to zero, the derivative of the Hall conductance with respect to m_f is proportional to ln(|m_f|), with the constant of proportionality being the ratio of the change of W at m_f = 0 to the energy gap in the initial state.</description></item><item><title>Effective time reversal and echo dynamics in the transverse field Ising model</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/2_ising_echo/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 14:40:01 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/2_ising_echo/</guid><description>The question of thermalisation in closed quantum many-body systems has received a lot of attention in the past few years. An intimately related question is whether a closed quantum system shows irreversible dynamics. However, irreversibility and what we actually mean by this in a quantum many-body system with unitary dynamics has been explored very little. In this work we investigate the dynamics of the Ising model in a transverse magnetic field involving an imperfect effective time reversal. We propose a definition of irreversibility based on the echo peak decay of observables. Inducing the effective time reversal by different protocols we find algebraic decay of the echo peak heights or an ever persisting echo peak indicating that the dynamics in this model is well reversible.</description></item><item><title>Dynamical Quantum Phase Transitions in the Kitaev Honeycomb Model</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/1_kitaev_dqpt/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 14:39:52 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/1_kitaev_dqpt/</guid><description>The notion of a dynamical quantum phase transition (DQPT) was recently introduced in [Heyl et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 110, 135704 (2013)] as the non-analytic behavior of the Loschmidt echo at critical times in the thermodynamic limit. In this work the quench dynamics in the ground state sector of the two-dimensional Kitaev honeycomb model are studied regarding the occurrence of DQPTs. For general two-dimensional systems of BCS-type it is demonstrated how the zeros of the Loschmidt echo coalesce to areas in the thermodynamic limit, implying that DQPTs occur as discontinuities in the second derivative. In the Kitaev honeycomb model DQPTs appear after quenches across a phase boundary or within the massless phase. In the 1d limit of the Kitaev honeycomb model it becomes clear that the discontinuity in the higher derivative is intimately related to the higher dimensionality of the non-degenerate model.</description></item><item><title>Quantum phase transition dynamics in the two-dimensional transverse-field Ising model</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/14_qkzm/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/14_qkzm/</guid><description>Based on simulations with tensor networks and neural quantum states we confirmed for the first time numerically the non-equilibrium scaling hypothesis of the Kibble-Zurek mechanism for a microscopic model system in two spatial dimensions.</description></item><item><title>Time-dependent variational principle for open quantum systems with artificial neural networks</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/16_open_tdvp/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/16_open_tdvp/</guid><description>By generalizing the time-dependent variational principle to a purely probabilistic formulation of quantum mechanics we developed a new approach to simulate the time-evolution of open quantum many-body systems using, e.g., autoregressive neural networks.</description></item><item><title>Quantum many-body dynamics in two dimensions with artificial neural networks</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/12_ann_dynamics/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Sep 2020 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/12_ann_dynamics/</guid><description>By developing a number of methodological advancements we demonstrated for the first time that neural quantum states are competitive with state-of-the-art tensor network techniques when simulating complex quantum dynamics in two spatial dimensions.</description></item></channel></rss>