<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Publications on Computational Quantum Science</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/</link><description>Recent content in Publications on Computational Quantum Science</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</managingEditor><webMaster>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 21:52:58 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Reinforcement learning entangling operations on spin qubits</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/32_spin_qubit_gates/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 21:52:58 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/32_spin_qubit_gates/</guid><description>&lt;p>High-fidelity control of one- and two-qubit gates past the error correction threshold is an essential ingredient for scalable quantum computing. We present a reinforcement learning (RL) approach to find entangling protocols for semiconductor-based singlet-triplet qubits in a double quantum dot. Despite the presence of realistically modelled experimental constraints, such as various noise contributions and finite rise-time effects, we demonstrate that an RL agent can yield performative protocols, while avoiding the model-biases of traditional gradient-based methods. We optimise our RL approach for different regimes and tasks, including training from simulated process tomography reconstruction of unitary gates, and investigate the nuances of RL agent design.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Learning to stabilize nonequilibrium phases of matter with active feedback using partial information</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/31_rl_circuit_game/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 21:49:48 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/31_rl_circuit_game/</guid><description>&lt;p>We investigate the role of information in active feedback control of quantum many-body systems using reinforcement learning. Active feedback breaks detailed balance, enabling the engineering of steady states and dynamical phases of matter otherwise inaccessible in equilibrium. We train reinforcement learning agents using partial state information to prevent entanglement spreading in (1+1)-dimensional stabilizer circuits with up to 128 qubits. We find that, above a critical information threshold, learned near-optimal strategies are non-greedy, stochastic, and reduce volume-law entangled steady states to area-law scaling. The agents achieve this by placing a series of bottlenecks that induce pyramidal structures in the long-time spatial entanglement distribution, which effectively split the system and reduce the maximum accessible entanglement. Crucially, learned strategies are inherently out of equilibrium and require real-time active feedback; we find that the learned behavior cannot be replaced by simple human-designed control rules. This work establishes the foundations for classically implemented, information-driven individual control of many interacting quantum degrees of freedom, demonstrating the capabilities of reinforcement learning to stabilize and uncover novel critical properties of many-body nonequilibrium steady states.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Simulating dynamics of correlated matter with neural quantum states</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/30_nqs_dynamics_book/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 06:40:00 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/30_nqs_dynamics_book/</guid><description>&lt;p>While experimental advancements continue to expand the capabilities to control and probe non-equilibrium quantum matter at an unprecedented level, the numerical simulation of the dynamics of correlated quantum systems remains a pivotal challenge - especially in intermediate spatial dimensions. Neural quantum states are emerging as a new computational tool to investigate the time evolution of many-body quantum systems in previously inaccessible regimes. We review the recent progress in the field with a focus on the different time propagation methods, an overview of the reported applications, and a discussion of the major current challenges.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Quantum computing and artificial intelligence: status and perspectives</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/29_aiqt/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 15:17:39 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/29_aiqt/</guid><description>&lt;p>This white paper discusses and explores the various points of intersection between quantum computing and artificial intelligence (AI). It describes how quantum computing could support the development of innovative AI solutions. It also examines use cases of classical AI that can empower research and development in quantum technologies, with a focus on quantum computing and quantum sensing. The purpose of this white paper is to provide a long-term research agenda aimed at addressing foundational questions about how AI and quantum computing interact and benefit one another. It concludes with a set of recommendations and challenges, including how to orchestrate the proposed theoretical work, align quantum AI developments with quantum hardware roadmaps, estimate both classical and quantum resources - especially with the goal of mitigating and optimizing energy consumption - advance this emerging hybrid software engineering discipline, and enhance European industrial competitiveness while considering societal implications.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Time evolution of the quantum Ising model in two dimensions using Tree Tensor Networks</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/28_ttn_tech/</link><pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 08:17:11 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/28_ttn_tech/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Many-body dynamics with explicitly time-dependent neural quantum states</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/27_tnqs/</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 07:45:41 +0100</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/27_tnqs/</guid><description>&lt;p>Simulating the dynamics of many-body quantum systems is a significant challenge, especially in higher dimensions where entanglement grows rapidly. Neural quantum states (NQS) offer a promising tool for representing quantum wavefunctions, but their application to time evolution faces scaling challenges. We introduce the time-dependent neural quantum state (t-NQS), a novel approach incorporating explicit time dependence into the neural network ansatz. This framework optimizes a single, time-independent set of parameters to solve the time-dependent Schrödinger equation across an entire time interval. We detail an autoregressive, attention-based transformer architecture and techniques for extending the model&amp;rsquo;s applicability. To benchmark and demonstrate our method, we simulate quench dynamics in the 2D transverse field Ising model and the time-dependent preparation of the 2D antiferromagnetic state in a Heisenberg model, demonstrating state of the art performance, scalability, and extrapolation to unseen intervals. These results establish t-NQS as a powerful framework for exploring quantum dynamics in strongly correlated systems.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Roughening dynamics of interfaces in two-dimensional quantum matter</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/26_roughening/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 12:01:49 +0100</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/26_roughening/</guid><description>We discovered, that the smooth-interface regime below the roughening transition of the two-dimensional quantum Ising model leads to prethermal plateauxin the non-equilibrium dynamics of domain wall initial conditions.</description></item><item><title>Neural Quantum States and Peaked Molecular Wave Functions: Curse or Blessing?</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/25_peaked_nqs/</link><pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2024 18:50:55 +0100</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/25_peaked_nqs/</guid><description>&lt;p>The field of neural quantum states has recently experienced a tremendous progress, making them a competitive tool of computational quantum many-body physics. However, their largest achievements to date mostly concern interacting spin systems, while their utility for quantum chemistry remains yet to be demonstrated. Two main complications are the peaked structure of the molecular wave functions, which impedes sampling, and large number of terms in second quantised Hamiltonians, which hinders scaling to larger molecule sizes. In this paper we address these issues jointly and argue that the peaked structure might actually be key to drastically more efficient calculations. Specifically, we introduce a novel algorithm for autoregressive sampling without replacement and a procedure to calculate a computationally cheaper surrogate for the local energy. We complement them with a custom modification of the stochastic reconfiguration optimisation technique and a highly optimised GPU implementation. As a result, our calculations require substantially less resources and exhibit more than order of magnitude speedup compared to the previous works. On a single GPU we study molecules comprising up to 118 qubits and outperform the ``golden standard&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo; CCSD(T) benchmark in Hilbert spaces of about 10^15 Slater determinants, which is orders of magnitude larger than what was previously achieved. We believe that our work underscores the prospect of NQS for challenging quantum chemistry calculations and serves as a favourable ground for the future method development.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Reinforcement learning pulses for transmon qubit entangling gates</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/24_transmon_rl/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Nov 2023 09:40:55 +0100</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/24_transmon_rl/</guid><description>&lt;p>The utility of a quantum computer depends heavily on the ability to reliably perform accurate quantum logic operations.
For finding optimal control solutions, it is of particular interest to explore model-free approaches, since their quality
is not constrained by the limited accuracy of theoretical models for the quantum processor - in contrast to many
established gate implementation strategies. In this work, we utilize a continuous-control reinforcement learning algorithm
to design entangling two-qubit gates for superconducting qubits; specifically, our agent constructs cross-resonance and CNOT
gates without any prior information about the physical system. Using a simulated environment of fixed-frequency,
fixed-coupling transmon qubits, we demonstrate the capability to generate novel pulse sequences that outperform the
standard cross-resonance gates in both fidelity and gate duration, while maintaining a comparable susceptibility to
stochastic unitary noise. We further showcase an augmentation in training and input information that allows our agent to
adapt its pulse design abilities to drifting hardware characteristics, importantly with little to no additional optimization.
Our results exhibit clearly the advantages of unbiased adaptive-feedback learning-based optimization methods for transmon
gate design.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Reconstructing effective Hamiltonians from nonequilibrium thermal and prethermal steady states</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/23_hamiltonian_reconstruction/</link><pubDate>Mon, 21 Aug 2023 09:06:28 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/23_hamiltonian_reconstruction/</guid><description>&lt;p>Reconstructing Hamiltonians from local measurements is key to enabling reliable quantum simulation: both validating the implemented model, and identifying any left-over terms with sufficient precision is a problem of increasing importance. Here we propose a deep-learning-assisted variational algorithm for Hamiltonian reconstruction by pre-processing a dataset that is diagnosed to contain thermal measurements of local operators. We demonstrate the efficient and precise reconstruction of local Hamiltonians, while long-range interacting Hamiltonians are reconstructed approximately. Away from equilibrium, for periodically and random multipolar driven systems, we reconstruct the effective Hamiltonian widely used for Floquet engineering of metastable steady states. Moreover, our approach allows us to reconstruct an effective quasilocal Hamiltonian even in the heating regime beyond the validity of the prethermal plateau, where perturbative expansions fail.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Highly resolved spectral functions of two-dimensional systems with neural quantum states</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/22_spectral_fun/</link><pubDate>Thu, 16 Mar 2023 13:07:08 +0100</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/22_spectral_fun/</guid><description>We developed a new approach to simulate spectral functions using neural quantum states, which for example accurately captures the gap closing at the phase transition of a two-dimensional quantum magnet despite the associated diverging time scale.</description></item><item><title>Wave function network description and Kolmogorov complexity of quantum many-body systems</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/21_wave_function_nets/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 08:56:04 +0100</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/21_wave_function_nets/</guid><description>&lt;p>Programmable quantum devices are now able to probe wave functions at unprecedented levels. This is based on the ability to project the many-body state of atom and qubit arrays onto a measurement basis which produces snapshots of the system wave function. Extracting and processing information from such observations remains, however, an open quest. One often resorts to analyzing low-order correlation functions - i.e., discarding most of the available information content. Here, we introduce wave function networks - a mathematical framework to describe wave function snapshots based on network theory. For many-body systems, these networks can become scale free - a mathematical structure that has found tremendous success in a broad set of fields, ranging from biology to epidemics to internet science. We demonstrate the potential of applying these techniques to quantum science by introducing protocols to extract the Kolmogorov complexity corresponding to the output of a quantum simulator, and implementing tools for fully scalable cross-platform certification based on similarity tests between networks. We demonstrate the emergence of scale-free networks analyzing data from Rydberg quantum simulators manipulating up to 100 atoms. We illustrate how, upon crossing a phase transition, the system complexity decreases while correlation length increases - a direct signature of build up of universal behavior in data space. Comparing experiments with numerical simulations, we achieve cross-certification at the wave-function level up to timescales of 4 μ s with a confidence level of 90%, and determine experimental calibration intervals with unprecedented accuracy. Our framework is generically applicable to the output of quantum computers and simulators with in situ access to the system wave function, and requires probing accuracy and repetition rates accessible to most currently available platforms.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Optimizing Design Choices for Neural Quantum States</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/20_nqs_gs_architectures/</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2023 09:19:57 +0100</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/20_nqs_gs_architectures/</guid><description>&lt;p>Neural quantum states are a new family of variational ansätze for quantum-many body wave functions with advantageous properties in the notoriously challenging case of two spatial dimensions. Since their introduction a wide variety of different network architectures has been employed to study paradigmatic models in quantum many-body physics with a particular focus on quantum spin models. Nonetheless, many questions remain about the effect that the choice of architecture has on the performance on a given task. In this work, we present a unified comparison of a selection of popular network architectures and symmetrization schemes employed for ground state searches of prototypical spin Hamiltonians, namely the two-dimensional transverse-field Ising model and the J1-J2 model. In the presence of a non-trivial sign structure of the ground states, we find that the details of symmetrization crucially influence the performance. We describe this effect in detail and discuss its consequences, especially for autoregressive models, as their direct sampling procedure is not compatible with the symmetrization procedure that we found to be optimal.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Discrete truncated Wigner approach to dynamical phase transitions in Ising models after a quantum quench</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/11_discrete_twa/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/11_discrete_twa/</guid><description>&lt;p>By means of the discrete truncated Wigner approximation we study dynamical phase transitions arising in the steady state of transverse-field Ising models after a quantum quench. Starting from a fully polarized ferromagnetic initial condition these transitions separate a phase with nonvanishing magnetization along the ordering direction from a symmetric phase upon increasing the transverse field. We consider two paradigmatic cases, a one-dimensional long-range model with power-law interactions \(\propto 1/r^\alpha\) decaying algebraically as a function of distance \(r\) and a two-dimensional system with short-range nearest-neighbour interactions. In the former case we identify dynamical phase transitions for \(\alpha\lesssim 2\) and we extract the critical exponents from a data collapse of the steady state magnetization for up to 1200 lattice sites. We find identical exponents for \(\alpha\lesssim 0.5\), suggesting that the dynamical transitions in this regime fall into the same universality class as the nonergodic mean-field limit. The two-dimensional Ising model is believed to be thermalizing, which we also confirm using exact diagonalization for small system sizes. Thus, the dynamical transition is expected to correspond to the thermal phase transition, which is consistent with our data upon comparing to equilibrium quantum Monte-Carlo simulations. We further test the accuracy of the discrete truncated Wigner approximation by comparing against numerically exact methods such as exact diagonalization, tensor network as well as artificial neural network states and we find good quantitative agreement on the accessible time scales. Finally, our work provides an additional contribution to the understanding of the range and the limitations of qualitative and quantitative applicability of the discrete truncated Wigner approximation.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Disorder-free localization in an interacting two-dimensional lattice gauge theory</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/10_disorder_free_localization/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/10_disorder_free_localization/</guid><description>&lt;p>Disorder-free localization has been recently introduced as a mechanism for ergodicity breaking in low-dimensional homogeneous lattice gauge theories caused by local constraints imposed by gauge invariance. We show that also genuinely interacting systems in two spatial dimensions can become nonergodic as a consequence of this mechanism. Specifically, we prove nonergodic behavior in the quantum link model by obtaining a rigorous bound on the localization-delocalization transition through a classical correlated percolation problem implying a fragmentation of Hilbert space on the nonergodic side of the transition. We study the quantum dynamics in this system by means of an efficient and perturbatively controlled representation of the wavefunction in terms of a variational network of classical spins akin to artificial neural networks. We identify a distinguishing dynamical signature by studying the propagation of line defects, yielding different light cone structures in the localized and ergodic phases, respectively. The methods we introduce in this work can be applied to any lattice gauge theory with finite-dimensional local Hilbert spaces irrespective of spatial dimensionality.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>From observations to complexity of quantum states via unsupervised learning</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/18_local_complexity/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/18_local_complexity/</guid><description>&lt;p>The vast complexity is a daunting property of generic quantum states that poses a significant challenge for theoretical treatment, especially in non-equilibrium setups. Therefore, it is vital to recognize states which are locally less complex and thus describable with (classical) effective theories. We use unsupervised learning with autoencoder neural networks to detect the local complexity of time-evolved states by determining the minimal number of parameters needed to reproduce local observations. The latter can be used as a probe of thermalization, to assign the local complexity of density matrices in open setups and for the reconstruction of underlying Hamiltonian operators. Our approach is an ideal diagnostics tool for data obtained from (noisy) quantum simulators because it requires only practically accessible local observations.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Irreversible dynamics in quantum many-body systems</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/6_irreversibility/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/6_irreversibility/</guid><description>&lt;p>Irreversibility, despite being a necessary condition for thermalization, still lacks a sound understanding in the context of isolated quantum many-body systems. In this work we approach this question by studying the behavior of generic many-body systems under imperfect effective time reversal, where the imperfection is introduced as a perturbation of the many-body state at the point of time reversal. Based on numerical simulations of the full quantum dynamics we demonstrate that observable echos occurring in this setting decay exponentially with a rate that is independent of the perturbation; hence, the sensitivity to perturbations is intrinsic to the system meaning that the dynamics is effectively irreversible.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>jVMC: Versatile and performant variational Monte Carlo leveraging automated differentiation and GPU acceleration</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/17_jvmc/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/17_jvmc/</guid><description>&lt;p>The introduction of Neural Quantum States (NQS) has recently given a new twist to variational Monte Carlo (VMC). The ability to systematically reduce the bias of the wave function ansatz renders the approach widely applicable. However, performant implementations are crucial to reach the numerical state of the art. Here, we present a Python codebase that supports arbitrary NQS architectures and model Hamiltonians. Additionally leveraging automatic differentiation, just-in-time compilation to accelerators, and distributed computing, it is designed to facilitate the composition of efficient NQS algorithms.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Learning the ground state of a non-stoquastic quantum Hamiltonian in a rugged neural network landscape</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/15_j1j2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/15_j1j2/</guid><description>&lt;p>Strongly interacting quantum systems described by non-stoquastic Hamiltonians exhibit rich low-temperature physics. Yet, their study poses a formidable challenge, even for state-of-the-art numerical techniques. Here, we investigate systematically the performance of a class of universal variational wave-functions based on artificial neural networks, by considering the frustrated spin-1/2 J1−J2 Heisenberg model on the square lattice. Focusing on neural network architectures without physics-informed input, we argue in favor of using an ansatz consisting of two decoupled real-valued networks, one for the amplitude and the other for the phase of the variational wavefunction. By introducing concrete mitigation strategies against inherent numerical instabilities in the stochastic reconfiguration algorithm we obtain a variational energy comparable to that reported recently with neural networks that incorporate knowledge about the physical system. Through a detailed analysis of the individual components of the algorithm, we conclude that the rugged nature of the energy landscape constitutes the major obstacle in finding a satisfactory approximation to the ground state wavefunction, and prevents learning the correct sign structure. In particular, we show that in the present setup the neural network expressivity and Monte Carlo sampling are not primary limiting factors.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Measuring complex partition function zeroes of Ising models in quantum simulators</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/8_fisher_zeros_qc/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/8_fisher_zeros_qc/</guid><description>&lt;p>Studying the zeroes of partition functions in the space of complex control parameters allows to understand formally how critical behavior of a many-body system can arise in the thermodynamic limit despite various no-go theorems for finite systems. In this work we propose protocols that can be realized in quantum simulators to measure the location of complex partition function zeroes of classical Ising models. The protocols are solely based on the implementation of simple two-qubit gates, local spin rotations, and projective measurements along two orthogonal quantization axes. Besides presenting numerical simulations of the measurement outcomes for an exemplary classical model, we discuss the effect of projection noise and the feasibility of the implementation on state of the art platforms for quantum simulation.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Quantum dynamics in transverse-field Ising models from classical networks</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/5_classical_nets/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/5_classical_nets/</guid><description>&lt;p>The efficient representation of quantum many-body states with classical resources is a key challenge in quantum many-body theory. In this work we analytically construct classical networks for the description of the quantum dynamics in transverse-field Ising models that can be solved efficiently using Monte Carlo techniques. Our perturbative construction encodes time-evolved quantum states of spin-1/2 systems in a network of classical spins with local couplings and can be directly generalized to other spin systems and higher spins. Using this construction we compute the transient dynamics in one, two, and three dimensions including local observables, entanglement production, and Loschmidt amplitudes using Monte Carlo algorithms and demonstrate the accuracy of this approach by comparisons to exact results. We include a mapping to equivalent artificial neural networks, which were recently introduced to provide a universal structure for classical network wave functions.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Quantum Many-Body Jarzynski Equality and Dissipative Noise on a Digital Quantum Computer</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/19_jarzynski/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/19_jarzynski/</guid><description>We explored fluctuations occuring in non-equilibrium processes implemented on a quantum processor, veryfying, for example, the Jarzynski equality in the regime of many interacting qubits.</description></item><item><title>Semiclassical echo dynamics in the Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev model</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/7_semiclassical_echoes/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/7_semiclassical_echoes/</guid><description>&lt;p>The existence of a quantum butterfly effect in the form of exponential sensitivity to small perturbations has been under debate for a long time. Lately, this question gained increased interest due to the proposal to probe chaotic dynamics and scrambling using out-of-time-order correlators. In this work we study echo dynamics in the Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev model under effective time reversal in a semiclassical approach. We demonstrate that small imperfections introduced in the time-reversal procedure result in an exponential divergence from the perfect echo, which allows to identify a Lyapunov exponent \( \lambda_L \). In particular, we find that \( \lambda_L \) is twice the Lyapunov exponent of the semiclassical equations of motion. This behavior is attributed to the growth of an out-of-time-order double commutator that resembles an out-of-time-order correlator.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Tripartite information, scrambling, and the role of Hilbert space partitioning in quantum lattice models</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/9_tripartite_info/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/9_tripartite_info/</guid><description>&lt;p>For the characterization of the dynamics in quantum many-body systems the question how information spreads and becomes distributed over the constituent degrees of freedom is of fundamental interest. The delocalization of information under many-body dynamics has been dubbed scrambling and out-of-time-order correlators were proposed to probe this behavior. In this work we investigate the time-evolution of tripartite information as a natural operator-independent measure of scrambling, which quantifies to which extent the initially localized information can only be recovered by global measurements. Studying the dynamics of quantum lattice models with tunable integrability breaking we demonstrate that in contrast to quadratic models generic interacting systems scramble information irrespective of the chosen partitioning of the Hilbert space, which justifies the characterization as scrambler. Without interactions the dynamics of tripartite information in momentum space reveals unambiguously the absence of scrambling.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Variational classical networks for dynamics in interacting quantum matter</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/13_vcn/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/13_vcn/</guid><description>&lt;p>Dynamics in correlated quantum matter is a hard problem, as its exact solution generally involves a computational effort that grows exponentially with the number of constituents. While a remarkable progress has been witnessed in recent years for one-dimensional systems, much less has been achieved for interacting quantum models in higher dimensions, since they incorporate an additional layer of complexity. In this work, we employ a variational method that allows for an efficient and controlled computation of the dynamics of quantum many-body systems in one and higher dimensions. The approach presented here introduces a variational class of wavefunctions based on complex networks of classical spins akin to artificial neural networks, which can be constructed in a controlled fashion. We provide a detailed prescription for such constructions and illustrate their performance by studying quantum quenches in one- and two-dimensional models. In particular, we investigate the nonequilibrium dynamics of a genuinely interacting two-dimensional lattice gauge theory, the quantum link model, for which we have recently shown &amp;ndash; employing the technique discussed thoroughly in this paper &amp;ndash; that it features disorder-free localization dynamics [P. Karpov et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 126, 130401 (2021)]. The present work not only supplies a framework to address purely theoretical questions but also could be used to provide a theoretical description of experiments in quantum simulators, which have recently seen an increased effort targeting two-dimensional geometries. Importantly, our method can be applied to any quantum many-body system with a well-defined classical limit.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Universal non-analytic behavior of the non-equilibrium Hall conductance in Floquet topological insulators</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/4_noneq_hall_2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 16:19:19 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/4_noneq_hall_2/</guid><description>&lt;p>We study the Hall conductance in a Floquet topological insulator in the long time limit after sudden switches of the driving amplitude. Based on a high frequency expansion of the effective Hamiltonian and the micromotion operator we demonstrate that the Hall conductance as function of the driving amplitude follows universal non-analytic laws close to phase transitions that are related to conic gap closing points, namely a logarithmic divergence for gapped initial states and jumps of a definite height for gapless initial states. This constitutes a generalization of the results known for the static systems to the driven case.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Universal nonanalytic behavior of the Hall conductance in a Chern insulator at the topologically driven nonequilibrium phase transition</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/3_noneq_hall_1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 16:16:15 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/3_noneq_hall_1/</guid><description>&lt;p>We study the Hall conductance of a Chern insulator after a global quench of the Hamiltonian. The Hall conductance in the long time limit is obtained by applying the linear response theory to the diagonal ensemble. It is expressed as the integral of the Berry curvature weighted by the occupation number over the Brillouin zone. We identify a topologically driven nonequilibrium phase transition, which is indicated by the nonanalyticity of the Hall conductance as a function of the energy gap m_f in the post-quench Hamiltonian H_f. The topological invariant for the quenched state is the winding number of the Green&amp;rsquo;s function W, which equals the Chern number for the ground state of H_f. In the limit that m_f goes to zero, the derivative of the Hall conductance with respect to m_f is proportional to ln(|m_f|), with the constant of proportionality being the ratio of the change of W at m_f = 0 to the energy gap in the initial state. This nonanalytic behavior is universal in two-band Chern insulators such as the Dirac model, the Haldane model, or the Kitaev honeycomb model in the fermionic basis.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Effective time reversal and echo dynamics in the transverse field Ising model</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/2_ising_echo/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 14:40:01 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/2_ising_echo/</guid><description>&lt;p>The question of thermalisation in closed quantum many-body systems has received a lot of attention in the past few years. An intimately related question is whether a closed quantum system shows irreversible dynamics. However, irreversibility and what we actually mean by this in a quantum many-body system with unitary dynamics has been explored very little. In this work we investigate the dynamics of the Ising model in a transverse magnetic field involving an imperfect effective time reversal. We propose a definition of irreversibility based on the echo peak decay of observables. Inducing the effective time reversal by different protocols we find algebraic decay of the echo peak heights or an ever persisting echo peak indicating that the dynamics in this model is well reversible.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Dynamical Quantum Phase Transitions in the Kitaev Honeycomb Model</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/1_kitaev_dqpt/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 14:39:52 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/1_kitaev_dqpt/</guid><description>&lt;p>The notion of a dynamical quantum phase transition (DQPT) was recently introduced in [Heyl et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 110, 135704 (2013)] as the non-analytic behavior of the Loschmidt echo at critical times in the thermodynamic limit. In this work the quench dynamics in the ground state sector of the two-dimensional Kitaev honeycomb model are studied regarding the occurrence of DQPTs. For general two-dimensional systems of BCS-type it is demonstrated how the zeros of the Loschmidt echo coalesce to areas in the thermodynamic limit, implying that DQPTs occur as discontinuities in the second derivative. In the Kitaev honeycomb model DQPTs appear after quenches across a phase boundary or within the massless phase. In the 1d limit of the Kitaev honeycomb model it becomes clear that the discontinuity in the higher derivative is intimately related to the higher dimensionality of the non-degenerate model. Moreover, there is a strong connection between the stationary value of the rate function of the Loschmidt echo after long times and the occurrence of DQPTs in this model.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Quantum phase transition dynamics in the two-dimensional transverse-field Ising model</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/14_qkzm/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/14_qkzm/</guid><description>Based on simulations with tensor networks and neural quantum states we confirmed for the first time numerically the non-equilibrium scaling hypothesis of the Kibble-Zurek mechanism for a microscopic model system in two spatial dimensions.</description></item><item><title>Time-dependent variational principle for open quantum systems with artificial neural networks</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/16_open_tdvp/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/16_open_tdvp/</guid><description>By generalizing the time-dependent variational principle to a purely probabilistic formulation of quantum mechanics we developed a new approach to simulate the time-evolution of open quantum many-body systems using, e.g., autoregressive neural networks.</description></item><item><title>Quantum many-body dynamics in two dimensions with artificial neural networks</title><link>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/12_ann_dynamics/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Sep 2020 16:20:41 +0200</pubDate><author>bWFya3VzLnNjaG1pdHRAZnotanVlbGljaC5kZQ== (Markus Schmitt)</author><guid>https://www.computational-quantum.science/publications/12_ann_dynamics/</guid><description>By developing a number of methodological advancements we demonstrated for the first time that neural quantum states are competitive with state-of-the-art tensor network techniques when simulating complex quantum dynamics in two spatial dimensions.</description></item></channel></rss>